<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached at St. Mary Spittle on Easter Tuesday 1613. By Roger Fenton D. in Diuinitie</title>
            <author>Fenton, Roger, 1565-1616.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1616</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 132 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 113 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A00669</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 10804</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S115028</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99850248</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99850248</idno>
            <idno type="VID">15437</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A00669)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 15437)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 794:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached at St. Mary Spittle on Easter Tuesday 1613. By Roger Fenton D. in Diuinitie</title>
                  <author>Fenton, Roger, 1565-1616.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 221, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by Eliot's Court Press?] for William Aspley,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1616.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name suggested by STC.</note>
                  <note>With 3 other sermons: "A sermon preached at Mercer chapell in Lent 1614" , "A sermon preached at the funerall of Mr. Iohn Stokele citizen and marchant-taylor of London" and "A sermon preached at the funerall of Mr. Iohn  Newman citizen and grocer of London"; each has separate dated title page; pagination and register are continuous.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Funeral sermons --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:15437:1"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:15437:1"/>
                  <p>A SERMON PREACHED AT. S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> MARY SPITTLE <hi>on Eaſter Tueſday</hi> 1613.</p>
                  <p>BY ROGER FENTON <hi>D. in Diuinitie.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <figure/>
                  <p>LONDON Printed for <hi>William Aſpley.</hi> 1616.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="sermon">
                  <pb facs="tcp:15437:2"/>
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:15437:2"/>
                  <epigraph>
                     <bibl>GALAT. 6. 7.</bibl>
                     <q>Be not deceiued, God is not mocked, for what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer a man ſoweth that ſhall he alſo reape.</q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE words as I haue read them are a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall inſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, abſolute in it ſelfe, ſpringing or growing of a particular precept in
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:15437:3"/> the former verſe, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine diuiding it ſelfe into ſeuerall heads in the verſes following. Let me conſider it a part by it ſelfe for intire: then if I dare I will tell you how it growes. In this place a preface to moue your attention I ſhall neede to vſe none; for my text it ſelfe is but a preface, and a propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; the preface doth prepare the heart with faith and reuerence to receiue the ſentence; <hi>be not deceiued God is not mocked,</hi> and you ſhall finde this that followeth to bee moſt true; that <hi>whatſoeuer a man ſoweth that ſhall he alſo reape.</hi> A
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:15437:3"/> ſaying whereupon the Holy Ghoſt hath repo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed more than ordinarie. It is but a plaine ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence; yea ſee, it preſents it ſelfe in the country method of ſowing and reaping, but it is a ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of that note as is not marked with a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon <hi>ecce,</hi> but ſet in the forehead with a double ſentence, <hi>be not deceiued.</hi> The <hi>preface</hi> then, and the <hi>propoſition,</hi> make the two parts of my text: the <hi>preface</hi> importeth thus much, that not to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace the truth of this ſaying is a dangerous er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, dangerous in two reſpects.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, becauſe it doth
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:15437:4"/> not deceiue others but our ſelues, yea our owne ſoules.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, it is a falla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie ſo much affected, ſo wilfull an errour, as is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported to bee the delu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of God himſelfe, who will not be mocked. Then followeth the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, and it followes vpon this preface. Firſt, as an vndoubted truth, that <hi>as a man ſoweth ſo he ſhall reape;</hi> and ſecondly, as a generall truth with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out exception, that <hi>what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer a man ſoweth that ſhall hee alſo reape.</hi> Of which and of the bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches in the ordering of my text, I will ſpeake by Gods holy aſſiſtance, &amp;
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:15437:4"/> your honorable &amp; chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian patience, ſo farre as the time will conſent, or the poore ſtrength of my ſpirit ſhall be able to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt. In thoſe many ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall places in the Epiſtles, where this word <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> is vſed for the error of the minde, it is no where ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken for any common er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, but for that which is a damnable, and fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damentall error ſeducing the ſoule vnto eternall perdition; and ſo I would deſire you to take it in this place, that you may take it to heart. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doth the Apoſtle ſpeake theſe words vnto thoſe that are without, but vnto Chriſtians, ſuch
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:15437:5"/> as had bin catechiſed, as it is in the former verſe, and brought vp in the boſome of the true Church, as you all are this day. How were they deceiued ſo groſely and dangerouſly? Euen by thoſe falſe teachers, that tooke to themſelues a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie &amp; boldnes to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe vnto their bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren a ſecret forme of religion, that ſo long as they kept within compas of the generall faith, ſo long as they did beleeue and profes the true faith of Chriſt, though they had certaine reſeruations by the way which were not alowable; yet that they might be ſaued not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding.
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:15437:5"/> Dealing and dallying with God Almighty, as <hi>Naaman</hi> the <hi>Aſſyrian</hi> did, <hi>God be</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">2. King. 5. 18.</note> 
                     <hi>mercifull vnto thy ſeruant in this point,</hi> in this dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling ſinne, in that reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued affection, herein God bee mercifull vnto thy ſeruant. The falla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie it ſelfe I finde in thoſe other places which ſhall ſerue for a ſit commenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie and doth fall directly vpon this text. The firſt, in the 6. chapter of the firſt Epiſtle to the Corin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians verſ. 9. <hi>Be not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued neither fornicators, nor Idolaters, nor adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, nor wantons, nor abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers of themſelues with mankind, nor theeues, nor</hi>
                     <pb n="8" facs="tcp:15437:6"/> 
                     <hi>drunkards, nor raylers, nor extortioners ſhall inherit the kingdome of God;</hi> the parallel with the 5. to the Epheſ: the 5, 6, verſes, <hi>This you know, that neither whoremonger nor vncleane perſon nor couetous perſon which is an Idolater hath any inheritance in the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Chriſt and of God. Let no man deceiue you with vaine words, for for ſuch things commeth the wrath of God vpon the children of diſobedience.</hi> It ſeemes there were ſome in the Church of Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinth, that were of <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rods</hi> religion, who thought that ſo long as he heard <hi>Iohn Baptiſt in many things gladly,</hi> hee might com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:15437:6"/> inceſt with his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers wife, and there were ſome in the Church of Epheſus, who were ſeduced by vaine teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, that ſowed pillowes vnder their elbowes, and drew the curtaines to lull them aſleepe, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded men out of the Stoikes Paradox, that all ſinnes were equall, alike mortall, and all alike ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niall, putting little diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence betweene ſinnes. Confounding infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties with ſinnes of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption, and ſaith the Apoſtle, for ſuch things commeth the wrath of God vpon the children of diſobedience, and to the Corinthians he ſaith,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:15437:7"/> Such as theſe, ſom of you were before you were in Chriſt, but now yee are waſhed, but now yee are ſanctified, but now yee are iuſtified in the name of the Lord, for ſuch as theſe cannot be actually true and naturall mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of Chriſt; they may crowde in amongſt vs, but they are not of vs: they may carry the name, and weare the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery, but they haue not the ſoules of true Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans; who while they are in the fleſh, all are ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, but yet not ſo groſſe ſinners as theſe; ſubiect they are to mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold infirmities, but not to preſumptuous ſinnes,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:15437:7"/> ſinne will dwell in them; it will liue in them, and ſometime it will tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nize ouer them, as in the firſt to the Rom. 7. 20. but it ſhall not raigne in their mortal bodies, they wil not yeeld the Scepter vnto it, and become vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntary ſubiects there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto. Rom. 6. 12. bad weeds wil grow in them, but they will not plow and ſow iniquity, as in the 22. of the Prouerbes verſe 8. The world will catch holde of them to make them (with the Prophets wife) to deſire one veſſell more, when all is full, as in 2. King. 4. 6. but euery couetous deſire to haue more, doth
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:15437:8"/> not exclude a man from heauen, but that coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe which is idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, which preferres a mans gaine before his God, which dares make ſhip-wracke of conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, rather then part with his golde. Such haue no inheritance in the kingdome of Chriſt nor of God, they that wil be rich fall into temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in 1. <hi>Tim</hi> 6. 9. not they that would be rich if it pleaſed God by good meanes; but they that will be rich, by hooke or by crooke; by <hi>Hophnies</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">1. Sam. 2<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 13. Abac. 1. 16.</note> fleſh-hooke, or the net, <hi>Habacuck</hi> ſpeaketh of, they ſhall fall into noy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome luſts that drowne
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:15437:8"/> men in perdition. The Apoſtle <hi>Iames</hi> hath yet an other maner of ſpeech in the firſt of his Epiſtle the 13. verſe, <hi>Let no man ſay when he is tempted that he is tempted of God,</hi> as if theſe ſeedes of temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on were of Gods ſowing, and not of our owne growing, &amp; ſo we might happily eſcape this bitter harueſt; <hi>erre not my deere brethren,</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Iames,</hi> for this is a dangerous errour; it is that imputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which old <hi>Adam</hi> by way of inſinuation laide vpon God, as if God had made him a wife for to tempt him; and it doth ſticke faſt in the hearts of many of his ſonnes vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:15437:9"/> this day; that in eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſinne that a man com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitteth, there is ſome fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall neceſſity from aboue, that driues him thereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, but if there had been no other booke written but that which euery one carries about him, in his owne boſome, it would conuince him of this errour. For my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience tells mee that I haue omitted many du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties which I might haue done, and haue commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted many ſinnes which I might haue left vndone, doth my conſcience erre in this accuſation or not? if it erre, how can it iuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be mine accuſer at the laſt day the 2. <hi>Rom.</hi> the 15
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:15437:9"/> if it erre not, then <hi>erre not my deare brethren</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Iames; bee not deceiued,</hi> ſaith my text, for there is no place for excuſe or extenuation, but as a man ſoweth ſo ſhall he alſo reape, be not deceiued; for if thou be, thou canſt not deceiue God; he is not mocked; is it not a mocke and an indignitie both for to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count the blood of Chriſt an vnholy thing? as if it had beene ſhed to <note place="margin">Heb. 10. 29.</note> waſh ſwine withall that delight to wallow in the mire, or dogges that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne backe againe vnto their vomit? Such ſinnes of recidiuation as thoſe wherof the Apoſtle ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth <note place="margin">Heb. 10. 26.</note>
                     <pb n="16" facs="tcp:15437:10"/> before, what is the reaſon, that the holy Ghoſt hath not recorded in the booke of God any one example, of any that receiued pardon &amp; was reſtored, for any groſſe ſinne by him committed that euer fell afterward into a relaps and was ſau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed? what is the reaſon of this? Surely becauſe it is to bee feared that the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance of ſuch a one was but a mock-repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance; the burned childe dreades the fire, and ſo will a true penitent ſhun that groſſe ſinne whereof hee hath had a true re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morſe. If this clauſe of my text ſhal ſeem obſcure vnto any, how God is
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:15437:10"/> mocked; this Citie will yeeld vs too large a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentary, for to make the ſame plaine vnto you A man with an ill purpoſe hath gotten &amp; doth keep an other mans goods in his poſſeſſion (no rare-example); his conſcience tells him, this is a great ſinne; for if others ſhould deale ſo by him he would be iuſtly &amp; greatly offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded; now for this ſinne amongſt the reſt, he doth aske and hope for par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don at Gods hand, as if he did repent, but it is but a mock-repentance, for ſaith S <hi>Auſtin</hi> a thiefe takes my purſe, he ſaith hee repenteth and doth aske pardone, but hee
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:15437:11"/> keepes my purſe, and holdes it ſtill, doth hee not mocke mee? I may put vp this flout becauſe I cannot remedie it, but God is not mocked, hee will haue iuſtice ſatisfied. So I vnderſtand my text. A Merchant liueth rio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſly not like the prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall Sonne, <hi>vpon his owne</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Luk. 15. 13. Luk. 16. 6.</note> 
                     <hi>portion,</hi> but as the vniuſt Steward, <hi>vpon other mens;</hi> in the end either for ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie, or in policie which is worſe, hee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes Bankerout, no rare example; he agrees with his Creditours for the halfe, for the third, yea for leſſe; he doth not obſerue the Prophets rule, <hi>firſt ſell, and pay, then</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">2. King 4. 7.</note>
                     <pb n="19" facs="tcp:15437:11"/> 
                     <hi>liue thou and thine on the rest,</hi> but firſt he reſerues a rich portion for him &amp; his, then he paies of the reſt, ſo the world is blin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, his Creditours are deluded, but God is not mocked; there will come a day when all recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings ſhall be caſt ouer a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, when iuſtice muſt bee ſatisfied to the full; then, ſhall this debter be caſt into priſon, that is, into a priſon out of which he ſhall not come, till hee haue paid the vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termoſt farthing, and yet ſhall not haue a farthing for to pay it. Therefore beloued in our Lord and Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt this wee doe ſay and affirme
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:15437:12"/> and I beſeech you for to carry it home with you, for one ſound point of doctrine, that the bloud of Chriſt was not ſhed vpon the Croſſe for to pay mens debts ciuilly vnderſtood: not becauſe it wanted vertue, for there is more vertue in the ſeede of the woman, then there can be poyſon in the head of the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent; but it is, becauſe that debt was paid vnto God, and not vnto men; It was becauſe thou couldeſt not performe the leaſt part of that price that was tendered vpon the croſſe; but this debt to thy Creditour thou maieſt; It was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:15437:12"/> by a counterfet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance thou hadſt made thy ſelfe vncapea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of pardon; and it was becauſe thou didſt offer an indignitie vnto thy bleſſed Sauiour, in ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting ſuch a reckoning vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his ſcore. Let mee conclude then in one word, theſe debts Chriſt doth not pay, for the reaſons alleaged, thou canſt and wilt not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge thy contracted debts; iuſtice one day muſt be ſatisfied vnto the full; therefore look thou to it, and looke to it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thou die, for after death comes iudgement. So I vnderſtand my text, let mee ſpeake vnto you
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:15437:13"/> beloued as the Apoſtle ſpeaketh in this place, not vnto thoſe that are with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, whom God ſhall iudge; but vnto thoſe that are in the Church, vnto you that call vpon the name of the Lord, who call Chriſt Lord as Profeſſours of the true Chriſtian religion; who as zealous Profeſſours of the ſame, can double it, and crie <hi>Lord, Lord;</hi> if any of you deſire to put off almighty God with a ſleight and a ſlie repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance for your great ſins committed againſt his diuine Maieſtie, or ſeeke to defraude his brother of his owne right and therein doth perſiſt, ſuch
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:15437:13"/> a one, doth but deceiue his owne ſoule, <hi>God is not mocked for as a man ſoweth ſo ſhall he alſo reape:</hi> Now this that hath beene ſaid it doth onely make way vnto that which follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, it is but a preface, be <hi>not deceiued, God is not mocked,</hi> &amp;c. Then wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in ſhould wee not be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued? what is that truth that we ſhould take ſo ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly to heart? whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer a man ſoweth that ſhal he alſo reape, a firme trueth without doubt, that as a man ſoweth ſo he ſhall reape; either the ſame in kinde, or the like in proportion; and it is a generall truth without exception, that <hi>whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer</hi>
                     <pb n="24" facs="tcp:15437:14"/> 
                     <hi>a man ſoweth</hi> either in kinde, or proportion hee ſhall be ſure to reape the ſame.</p>
                  <p>To beginne with the firſt, and firſt in kinde: the very inference of this ſentence vpon the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face doth argue a very pregnant inſtance, that whoſoeuer doth goe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to delude or mock God, as hath before bin ſaid, hee ſhall finde, that in the end God will mock him; he that ſits in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen ſhall laugh him to ſcorne, and the Lord ſhal haue him in deriſion the 2. Pſalme the 4. verſe: he ſhall reape the ſame at Gods hand.</p>
                  <p>Againe, <hi>Salomon</hi> go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:15437:14"/> about to perſwade the young man to ſow his ſeede betime in the morning, the 11. of the Preacher the 6. verſe, the ſeedes of vertue in the morning of his youth; the young gallant is not diſpoſed; he is no fit au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditour of that doctrine; he hopes for to liue ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny yeeres; and in them all to reioyce, as it is at the 8. verſe. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if wee come to vrge his conſcience ſo ſoone, hee thinkes of vs, as the Diuell ſayd to Chriſt, that we are come to tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment him before his time; But <hi>Salomon</hi> telles him, that though he liue many yeeres, yet they
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:15437:15"/> are but vanity, and they come to the end of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; he cannot preuaile with his many yeeres, marke what followeth at the 9. verſe, ſaith GOD by <hi>Salomon,</hi> Reioyce oh youngman in thy youth, let thy heart cheere thee in thy yoong dayes, ſo God ſayth, but hee doth but mocke him, for if God laugh, it is time for the young man to weep, for there followeth a moſt fearefull <hi>Cataſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phe:</hi> for <hi>know and bee thou ſure, that for all theſe things GOD ſhall bring thee to iudgement.</hi> But moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellently and fit for this purpoſe, is that that wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom herſelfe deliuereth,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:15437:15"/> or rather GOD, who is wiſdome it ſelfe, in the firſt of the Prouerbes at the 20. verſe, ſhee calleth without, ſhe vttereth her voyce in the ſtreets, ſhee ſtretcheth out her hands in the high ſtreet among the preſſe of the people, and vttereth her words in the city, the 21. verſe, as if he had ſayd in your Churches, at the Croſſe, or in theſe places, and <note place="margin">The Spit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle.</note> what be her words? be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I haue called, and you refuſed, becauſe I haue ſtretched out mine hand and none would regard, yea, deſpiſed my counſels &amp; would none of my corrections, at the 24. verſe, Therefore I
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:15437:16"/> will laugh at your deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; when feare com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth like ſudden deſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and your miſery and deſtruction like a whirle-winde, when affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and anguiſh ſhall come vpon you, then ſhall they call, but I will not anſwer, they ſhall ſeeke me earely, but they ſhall not find me. Marke theſe that mocke God, how God mockes them againe; For they reape the ſame in kinde, they would not heare him, when hee preached vnto them in their health, therefore God will not heare them when they ſhall pray to him in their ſickeneſſe: they heard
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:15437:16"/> God preaching by his word out of the pulpet, but they would not obey, therefore God ſhall heare them cry from their death-beds, but hee will not anſwer them, they ſhall ſeek him early, but ſhall not finde him, and as they ſowed ſo ſhall they reape; the ſame in kinde, if not the like in proportion, as you may reade the quality of the ſinne in the nature of Gods puniſhments, be it temporall or bee it eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, if temporall, looke vpon the roote, was not <hi>Adams</hi> temporal puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t well fitted to his fal? He did eat in wantonnes, hee ſhall now eat in ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:15437:17"/> 
                     <hi>in ſorrow ſhalt thou eat of it all the dayes of thy life:</hi> The ſhame of his ſoule it was the ſin of his ſoule, it was expreſſed in the nakedneſſe of his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy. His aſpiring minde in affecting to bee aboue a man, was pulled downe ſo low, that he was behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the poore beaſts for a couering, and we his ſonnes, if our coats be of wooll, the ſheepe wore them firſt; if of ſilke, the poore ſilke-worme may pull downe our pride. The hardneſſe of <hi>Adams</hi> fore-head, in excuſing and defending his ſinne ſo obſtinately before God, face to face, was well diſſolued into the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:15437:17"/> ſweat of his browes; his brow alſo remaining the ſeate of ſhame. That ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary delight the woman tooke in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden fruit, multiplied her ſorrowes. Oh it was pleaſing vnto the eye, in the 3. of Geneſis the 6: therefore the eye is the catarract and floud-gate of ſorrow; ſorrow ſhall remaine in her eyes more than ordinarie. She had a longing deſire to that fruit, oh the fruit in the middeſt of the garden worth all the reſt; and what elſe is the reaſon that ſo many quames and vnnaturall longings are yet in that ſexe. Shee ſo abuſed her liberty in
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:15437:18"/> ouer-ruling her husband, to whom before ſhee was ſweetly ſubordinat with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out renitencie; therefore now, will ſhee, nill ſhee, ſhee muſt be ſubiect, and hee muſt rule ouer her. Looke vpon the tree that ſpringeth out of this root. A deluge of ſinne ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flowed the old world, which brought a deluge of water to waſh the ſame, and that which the water cannot waſh the fire ſhall purge. Behold the builders of Babels Tower conſpired againſt heauen; therefore were they ſcattred vpon the earth By that conſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie they had thought to haue gotten them a
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:15437:18"/> name; therefore God makes them ſo ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, that one man knowes not an others language, and all this in the very tongue, which is the very inſtrument and trumpet of fame. And that burning luſt of the Sodomites was fitly pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed with fire from heauen; that vnnaturall luſt, with vnnaturall fire and brimſtone from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen; that now it remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth a monument of that their filthy abomination vntill this day.</p>
                  <p>I could hold you too long in the proportion of Gods iudgements vnto the ſinnes of Countries and Nations. As of the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:15437:19"/> Egyptians, the Edo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mites, the Cananites, the Iewes themſelues for kil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ling the Lord of life, whoſe bloud according vnto their owne impre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation is remayning vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their children vnto this day. But that which is perſonall is more ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble to euery one of vs, and commeth home to my text, <hi>that as a man ſoweth, ſo ſhall he alſo reap,</hi> either the ſame in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, or he ſhall reape the ſame in kinde; an eye for eye, a tooth for a tooth, a toe for a toe; 70 <hi>Kings</hi> (ſaith Adonibezek) <hi>with their thumbs and toes cut off, haue eaten meat vnder my table, iuſt as I delt with</hi>
                     <pb n="35" facs="tcp:15437:19"/> 
                     <hi>them ſo hath God delt with me,</hi> the 1 of Iudges the 7. If not the ſame in kinde, yet in exact proportion, as <hi>Abels</hi> bloud cryed for vengance againſt his vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naturall brother. Nature was offended, nature will be reuenged; as in the 4. of Geneſis at the 2. verſe, <hi>Thou ſhalt till the ground and hence-forth ſhee ſhall not yeeld thee her naturall ſtrength.</hi> Becauſe <hi>Cain</hi> would not afford an abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding place for <hi>Abel</hi> vpon the earth, therefore the earth would not afford an abiding place for <hi>Cain, a vagabond and a runna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate ſhalt thou be vpon the earth.</hi> That wicked <hi>Cham</hi> the ſpot of nature
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:15437:20"/> who againſt naturall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence diſhonoured his father <hi>Noah,</hi> was accur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in his owne ſonne, whoſe graceles poſteritie, the Cananites, (for <hi>Cham</hi> was the father of <hi>Canaan</hi> Gen: 9. 18) giuen ouer to all vnnaturall vice be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came natures vomit in the 18 of Leuiticus, <hi>the land ſpued them out,</hi> v. 28 For a remembrance of that vnfaithful ſoule that would beleeue no more of Gods iudgments than ſhee ſaw with her eyes, there ſtands a pillar of ſalt depriued of all ſenſe for abuſing her ſenſe in looking backe, for an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting monument; &amp; for an example of Gods
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:15437:20"/> iudgment, to ſalt and ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon all poſterities to take heede of back<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>ſliding in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſinne. She might pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend that ſhee looked backe to encourage her two daughters that fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed her, but becauſe her heart followed her eye backe againe into Sodome, therefore was this puniſhment vpon her, as a dreadfull docu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to anſwer all turne-backs vnto ſinne, that they ſhall not haue Gods grace to ſtep one foote forward to the ſeruice of God. Nay the ſeruants of God who haue obtai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned pardon vpon their true repentance, God doth notwithſtanding
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:15437:21"/> proportion his temporal puniſhments vnto their ſinnes, to teach vs that none of vs ſhall euer be any gainers by ſinning. Was not <hi>Dauids</hi> adultery wel rewarded in <hi>Abſolons</hi> folly with his Fathers Concubines? And for his murder of <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>riah,</hi> the ſword was not to depart from his houſe all the daies of his life. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe his ſonne <hi>Salomon</hi> diuided Gods kingdome and religion, betweene God and Idols, therfore God diuided his king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome between <hi>Rehoboam</hi> and <hi>Ieroboam.</hi> And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe his ſonne <hi>Rehoboam</hi> would neede be a yoke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maker to oppreſſe <hi>Iſrael,</hi>
                     <pb n="39" facs="tcp:15437:21"/> ſo as his little finger ſhould be bigger, than his fathers loynes; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God brought it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout that his loynes were no bigger than his fathers finger, by cutting off, of ten Tribes at one blow. So I haue giuen you a taſte, and but a taſte of this truth, in the roote, in the tree, and in the branches: in nations, &amp; in perſons that be repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brate, &amp; in the true ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of God; but theſe are but temporall iudgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, God tempers all his iudgments; they be like our <hi>quarter Seſſions;</hi> here and there ſome are ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iudged in this world for examples ſake, and as <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaith in the 58.
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:15437:22"/> Pſalme, the laſt verſe, that men may ſay, <hi>doubtleſſe there is a God that iudgeth in the earth.</hi> For as <hi>S. Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin</hi> hath well obſerued, if all ſinners ſhould bee puniſhed in this world, wee ſhould feare no far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther iudgement; and if none at all, wee ſhould doubt of Gods proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, in the firſt booke <hi>de Ciuitate Dei</hi> the 8. Therefore there ſhall come a day when this my text ſhall be fulfilled <hi>in plenitudine,</hi> in weight, number, and meaſure, in a moſt exact propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; when the deniall of a crum of bread vnto poore <hi>Lazarus,</hi> ſhall bee requited with a deniall
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:15437:22"/> of a drop of water in hell fire; When the vialls of Gods vengance ſhall bee powred out in full mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure vpon damned ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits. When infinite tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments ſhall bee inflicted vpon ſinners for their ſins; which as the haires of their heads are innu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merable and infinite, ſo ſhall the puniſhment bee vpon obſtinate ſinners a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt that diuine maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie which is infinite; And vpon impenitent ſinners for fruſtrating and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king voide that price of their redemption, which is infinite. And vpon thoſe vngratefull wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, who haue made ſo little reckoning of the
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:15437:23"/> graces and bleſſings of God towards mankinde, which are infinite. And as infinite torments ſhall be inflicted proportio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable vnto their infinite ſins committed againſt God; ſo likewiſe the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of our manifold duties, ſhall there be pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed with an vtter de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priuation of all comfort: there ſhall be vtter dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and no mitigation of torments, no not for a moment; Where the tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentors are ſpirits and cannot be weary; where the worme ſhall euer gnaw, and neuer dye: where the fire ſhall bee vnquenchable neuer go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out; where the breath
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:15437:23"/> of the Lord like a ſtream of brimſton doth kindle it, Eſay 30. 33. there ſhall bee no hope of deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance (and yet were it not for hope the heart would burſt) no, there ſhall be no hope, yet the heart muſt hold a roote of immortalitie, conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually feeding both ſoule and body vnto e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall death. What re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy then but patience? Nay, no patience nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; who can dwell with euerlaſting burning, where ſhall bee weeping and gnaſhing of teeth, and not loſe his patience? ſeing that gnaſhing of teeth is an effect of an impatient furie. But alas,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:15437:24"/> replies the vnfaithfull ſinner, what proportion is here? Shall I be puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed with eternall tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, for my momenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie ſins? euerlaſting bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning for a few yeares ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning? what proportion? Verily a moſt exact pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion; for hee that doth delight in ſinne, doth deſire that thoſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights of his, might con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue if it were poſſible for euer; now ſaith S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                     <hi>Bernard</hi> the very deſire of ſinning is ſinne it ſelfe, before God; therefore an infinite deſire ſhall be eternally puniſhed. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, that of <hi>S. Gregorie</hi> (I take it) is well groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, he that dyeth with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:15437:24"/> repentance, iuſtice doth preſuppoſe that if that man could haue li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued for euer, hee would haue ſinned for euer; if thou then wilt offend thy God <hi>in aeternitudine,</hi> that is, ſo long as thou liueſt, then God will iuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly puniſh thee <hi>in aeterno,</hi> that is, ſo long as God himſelfe liueth, for euer and euer. For thoſe, that will ſinne againſt God, ſo long as they haue any being in this world, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out repentance; they ſhal be puniſhed by God, ſo long as they ſhall haue any being in the world to come, without mercy. The contrary doth illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate and proue both;
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:15437:25"/> whoſoeuer continueth to the end he ſhall be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, ſaith the text: By what proportion? Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe God in mercy doth preſuppoſe, that that man if he had liued for euer would haue continued for euer in well doing. Therefore as God in his iuſt mercy doth crowne our perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerance with immortali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie; ſo likewiſe in his moſt iuſt iudgment ſhall he puniſh finally all im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penitencie with eternall vengeance, iuſt as a man ſoweth ſo ſhall hee alſo reape in moſt exact pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion. And let this ſerue for the truth of this propoſition.</p>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:15437:25"/>
                  <p> Now followeth the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall to bee examined, <hi>whatſoeuer a man ſoweth, that ſhall hee alſo reape.</hi> Whatſoeuer; be it good, or bad; be it ſowen to the fleſh, or to the ſpirit, which is the Apoſtles di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtribution in the verſe following. If to the fleſh; then is it generall with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out exception, that what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer is ſowen turneth to corruption and to our confuſion, as <hi>Hoſea</hi> ſaith cap: 8. 7. they ſow the winde, and ſhall reape the whirlewinde. Their roote is rottenneſſe and their bud duſt, <hi>Eſay</hi> 5. 24. But marke the phraſe, <hi>Quicquid ſeminaverit ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo: Whatſoeuer a man</hi>
                     <pb n="48" facs="tcp:15437:26"/> 
                     <hi>ſhall ſow.</hi> For there are ſome weeds which grow of themſelues naturally, without ſowing; others about which wee take paines and imploy our ſelues with all induſtrie, and are of our owne ſow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. As <hi>S. Bernard</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt his ſentences like wiſe expoundeth, <hi>ſemine tuo, i. e. operibus tuis:</hi> cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the deeds which wee doe, the <hi>ſeede which wee ſow.</hi> And Ioh. 8. 44. our Sauiour ſaith, that when the Deuill ſpeaketh a lye, <hi>de ſuo loquitur,</hi> hee ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth that which is as it were of his owne ſowing and growing.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. As for thoſe weeds which grow vp in vs with
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:15437:26"/> out our ſowing, if ſo be that they diſpleaſe vs, as they did the Apoſtle in the 7. to the Romans, verſe 24 <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>O wretched man that I am who ſhall deliuer me from the bodie of this death?</hi> if we finde in our ſelues a loathing of our ſinnes, or of our ſelues for ſinne: If we be vexed at the ſoule for our owne ſinnes as the Cananitiſh womans daughter was <note place="margin">Matth. 15. 22.</note> for her diuell: if wee la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to ſuppreſſe them; and learne of our Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine Chriſt in the 3. of Gen: verſ. 15. to ſtrike at ſinne in vs, ſo ſoone as euer it begins to put out the head; If wee daſh
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:15437:27"/> theſe Babyloniſh Brats againſt the ſtones whiles they bee young <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 137. 9. (for ſinne is a net<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, it muſt not be dallied withall, or tenderly han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dled, for then will it ſtinge vs,) if wee doe la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour I ſay to weede out theſe ſinnes that grow in vs; then God is mercifull to paſſe them ouer, for <hi>if thou Lord ſhouldeſt marke what is done amiſſe who ſhould be able to abide it?</hi> we ſhould reap then no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but gall and bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, if we do that which we would not do then it is not we, ſaith the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, but ſinne that dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth in vs, ſinne that is preſent with vs, ſin that
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:15437:27"/> growes in vs naturally without any ſowing.</p>
                  <p>But on the other ſide if wee plow and ſow ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity; if we doe <hi>imagine miſchiefe vpon our beds,</hi> as <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaith; if we do ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die to bee naught, and take great paines to doe wickedly as <hi>Ieremie</hi> ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth cap. 9. 5. if we break vp the fallowes and fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes of our hearts vnto ſinne; and make our eies Brokers vnto the heart of iniquity; if we go and buy ſtrange ſeedes at the Theater; and (I tremble to ſpeake it) fetch home new faſhions from the houſe of God; if we doe delight to bee merrie in impiety, and to animate
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:15437:28"/> and ſtir vp one another as the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> ſpeaketh the 56. chap. the laſt verſ. <hi>Come I will bring wine and wee will fill our ſelues with ſtrong drinke, to morrow ſhall be as this day and much more aboundant:</hi> then what is this but to plow and ſow and water wickedneſſe; and then ſhall wee be ſure to reape a moſt ranke harueſt?</p>
                  <p>If it bee good ſeede that wee ſow, we ſhall be ſure to reape the ſame at the hand of God whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer it be, whether it bee beneuolence vnto men, or deuotion vnto God, be it ſowne neuer ſo ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretly; the cloſer the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, <hi>thy father which ſeeth</hi>
                     <pb n="53" facs="tcp:15437:28"/> 
                     <hi>thee in ſecret ſhall reward thee openly.</hi> Whatſoeuer a man ſoweth there is an other difference in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of God; For God doth ſowe much good ſeede amongſt vs and he reapes little or nothing at all. When his ſon Chriſt, did ſow his ſeed himſelfe with a moſt skilful hand, ſome fell by the way ſide and wanting good mold to couer it, it was quickly taken away, that is, the people would preſſe and throng one another in the gates, and flocke vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his Sermons, but it was out of curioſitie or for formalitie (like theſe times) a ſolemn hearing, and a ſolemne forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:15437:29"/> Some fell in ſtonie ground, and was well bladed, but not well roo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, &amp; therefore quickly faded, that is, ſo long as the loaues laſted, ſo long as the Miniſters of Chriſt did fill their bellies they heard the word with cheerefulnes and alacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie; but when the Sunne of perſecution aroſe, they withered, when the croſſe came they fled. Some fell amongſt thornes which choaked his good ſeede; yea and perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the Sonne of God the ſeed-man of the word, with great ſharpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe &amp; bitternes. Now if the ſonne himſelfe had no better ſucceſſe no
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:15437:29"/> maruell though his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants haue great cauſe to complain, with the three great Prophets of God with <hi>Eſay</hi> in the 49. the 4. verſe <hi>I haue laboured in vaine and for nothing, our iudgement is with the Lord and my workes with my God:</hi> with <hi>Ezechiel</hi> the 33. and 32. verſe whoſe Sermons were <hi>like the ſongs of one that could ſing well and had a pleaſant voice, for they heard him but they did not vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand;</hi> as if we were cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led vnto theſe places on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to tickle and fill your eares with a tickling phraſe or plauſible elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence. With the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Ieremie</hi> the 6. chap.
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:15437:30"/> the 29. verſe, who com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaines, <hi>that his bellowes are burned, that the lead is conſumed, and the fire hath melted in vaine,</hi> it ſeemes hee had gotten the conſumption of the lungs amongſt them; he had burnt a hole in his bellowes, had ſpent his Spirit, and laboured in vaine. Thus, I ſay, God doth plow and ſow, and call to his people by his ſonne, by the Prophets, by his miniſters, he look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for fruit, and behold hedge<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>fruite; ſuch as the heathens bring foorth &amp; ſcarce ſo good; he wait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for grapes and behold <hi>labr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ae</hi> wild grapes. But now whatſoeuer good
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:15437:30"/> thing a man ſhall ſow vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God, he ſhall bee ſure to reap the ſame at Gods hand whatſoeuer it bee; be it ſowne in pietie, or ſowne in charitie; in pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, to the mainetenance of Gods ſeruants; or in charity to our brethren, whether it be giuen to a Prophet in the name of a Prophet; or to the poore in the name of Chriſt; it ſhall haue a Prophets reward, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare his ſoule in this life and a kingdome for to crowne him in the life to come, thats for the qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie.</p>
                  <p>So likewiſe for the quantitie whatſoeuer a man ſoweth be it little or
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:15437:31"/> much; the 9. of the 2. Corinth. the 6. verſe, <hi>He that ſoweth ſparingly ſhall reape ſparingly, hee that ſoweth bountifully ſhall alſo reape bountifully,</hi> both ſhal be Reapers according to the quantity be it little or much whatſoeuer is ſowne; if it be ſowne with the right hand; if it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuen in the right name; be it more or leſſe, hee ſhall reape the ſame at Gods hands from a cup of cold water vnto the erecting of Hoſpitalls; from a crumme of bread giuen to poore <hi>Lazarus</hi> at your gates, vnto the continuall feeding and cloathing of ſuch as theſe littly-great friends well
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:15437:31"/> purchaſed by Mammon. If ye will liſten to the ad<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uice of our Sauiour Chriſt, who is wiſedome it ſelfe, he tells you, that you cannot make better vſe of your wealth nor make a better purchaſe, then to purchaſe ſuch friends as theſe. Then by his aduice, <hi>let vs bee ſtrong in well doing,</hi> and encouraged by the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of others, for whom wee are to praiſe God, &amp; bleſſe his name, for ſending downe his gracious Spirit and mou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the hearts of many in this kind, as you heard the laſt day.</p>
                  <p>Theſe and others pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent themſelues at this
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:15437:32"/> time like <hi>Lazarus</hi> in <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brahams</hi> boſome; a moſt heauenly ornament vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this City, and they ſhal riſe likwiſe at the laſt day not to condemne but to commend and by their publike teſtimony be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore men and Angells to receiue their good Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factors into thoſe euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting Tabernacles. This ſhall be the thankefulnes theſe friends ſhall return if you will make the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe. Let vs therefore bee moued by the wiſe counſell of our bleſſed Sauiour, and ſo vſe theſe temporall bleſſings that God hath beſtowed vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vs; as wee may ſtill liue in hope of that bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:15437:32"/> ſentence at the laſt day, <hi>Come ye bleſſed of my Father inherit the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome prepared for you.</hi> Why? becauſe yee haue clothed the naked, and fed the hungrie; doing it vnto them, is as vnto my ſelfe. And let vs be aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured of the truth of this my text; that whatſoeuer wee doe ſowe, little or much; we ſhall be ſure to reape the ſame.</p>
                  <p>Here right honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, right worſhipfull and beloued in our Sauiour Chriſt, I would very gladly haue made an end, but as I haue view<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed my text a part by it ſelfe, ſo is it my part to ſet it in frame as I found it;
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:15437:33"/> and then I muſt of neceſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſitie fall vpon a point, which I may not touch without a preface. I haue broken the rule of me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod in making that an Appendix which ſhould haue beene an exordium and entrance vnto my ſpeech; becauſe I thought that if the time would haue cut of any thing it ſhould cut of that, if I ſhould balke it, or wilful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly omit it. Here be many Schollers and Diuines preſent, that would ſay, I came not cloſe home to my text: And when I am come to it, my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience tells me, that true preaching is to carrie the text home to your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences.
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:15437:33"/> Let me ingenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly confes vnto you, that when I firſt pitch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed my meditation vpon this ſentence, I did not at all thinke of the wordes immediately going be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, which now I muſt needes read vnto you, for they are the very key that open my text; <hi>let him that is taught in the word, make him that hath taught him partaker of all his goods. Be not deceiued God is not mocked for whatſoeuer a man ſoweth that ſhall hee alſo reape.</hi> The words are plaine e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough without a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentary; let him that is taught in the word, be he whatſoeuer, (ſo hee be
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:15437:34"/> taught in the word) let him make <hi>him,</hi> not <hi>them;</hi> though them alſo as oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion ſhall require; (for the Galathians no doubt had many Teachers, as wee alſo haue) but make <hi>him</hi> eſpecially, who hath the cure and charge of thy ſoule Partaker of all thy goods; This is the Apoſtles precept.</p>
                  <p>But if thou ſeekeſt ſhifts, and deuices to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraud him; thou thinkeſt thou deceiueſt him, but thou deceiueſt thy ſelfe; Be not deceiued; for though thou be, yet thou canſt not deceiue God, it is his portion, it is ſet a part for the maintenance of his ſeruice, and God
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:15437:34"/> will not bee mocked. whatſoeuer thou ſoweſt in this kinde thou ſhalt alſo reape. You ſee, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued, how this Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture falls, and I am afraid it falls heauie vpon many in this City.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Be not deceiued,</hi> firſt in confounding <hi>beneuolence</hi> and duty, there is a ſuttle fallacie in theſe tearmes and in theſe our times. <hi>Beneuolance</hi> is like their <hi>free-will offrings</hi> of olde: and <hi>duties</hi> as their <hi>ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie oblation. Beneuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence</hi> doth remit the quantity of the gift and the comfort of the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to whom it is giuen, vnto the liberality of the Benifactors; But <hi>duties</hi>
                     <pb n="66" facs="tcp:15437:35"/> they doe preſcribe, and limit, &amp; cut by a thread. For the firſt, this place, where now we are aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled is to bee commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and this will reckon and renowne you a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the vertuous of this City; but this is not the point of my text. The Apoſtle ſpeaketh of an other kinde; Wee praiſe God for this, and bleſſe him for the <hi>bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uolence</hi> of many, vnto di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers: But as a dutie of all, vnto all thoſe whom God, in his prouidence, hath ſet ouer their ſoules, is that whereof the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſpeaketh. This appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth in the 9. of the firſt to the <hi>Corinthians</hi> verſ. 4.
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:15437:35"/> 
                     <hi>Haue wee not power?</hi> that is, haue we not right as a dutie belonging vnto vs? that milke that the flock doth owe to the Feeder; that fruit that the vine giues to the planter, is (in that place) that por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which God takes to himſelfe if it be withheld from him, he counts it a mocking of him. Let thoſe (Beloued) who haue not in this kinde vrged the purſes of any, nor hope that they euer ſhall, let them haue leaue, ſomething more freely, to diſcharge their conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences herein.</p>
                  <p>What is the part then, the Apoſtle meanes or alludeth vnto in this
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:15437:36"/> place? is it that portion which God alotted vnto the <hi>Leuites</hi> vnder the law? No, by no meanes; that were too much; for the <hi>Leuites</hi> had, beſides their tithes and offrings, beſide their firſt fruits, ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices and vowes; they had 48. walled Cities, with large Suburbs for their cattle; large glebes to plant and ſowe in; when as their whole land, was not ſo bigge as the third part of <hi>England,</hi> what then, is it preciſely the tenth part, which God doth challendge to himſelfe in mount <hi>Sina</hi> the 27. of <hi>Leuit.</hi> the 32. almoſt 430 yeares before the <hi>Leuits</hi> had any part?
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:15437:36"/> no by no meanes, that were too much; how then? is it any part at all, of all thy goods? Verily thus much is agreed vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, of all ſides; (for now I muſt touch no contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſies) this I ſay is agreed vpon vnder the Goſpell, that the Church of Chriſt, after that it was once erected, did in her continuall practiſe accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the very letter of Saint <hi>Paules</hi> text in this place, determine a porti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, be it what it will be, a portion I ſay in all thy goods, the reaſon was, that the Paſtor and the people might ſtand, and fall together: that hee might haue compaſſion
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:15437:37"/> of thy loſſe, as well as comfort in thy encreaſe; both alike depending vpon the prouidence of God; that he might pray as affectionately in a ſtorme as the Marchant; and praiſe God in time of ſafety alſo. Why, ſo hee ſhould doe howſoeuer; yet becauſe we are men, and not Angels; the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God thought it meet to encourage them by allotting a portion both in towne and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie, out of all thy goods. So ſaith <hi>Paul</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</p>
                  <p>Yea but ye will ſay put out that ſame <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> and wee will compound with you by houſe-rent, ſo
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:15437:37"/> ſhall you be at a certaine; exchange is no Church-robery, the Law hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined it, true and in great wiſedome, for the law muſt of neceſſity, to preuent many miſchifes, it muſt, I ſay, leaue ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny things vnto the liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of thy conſcience, for to bee anſwered in a higher Court. Wilt thou performe no more duties to God nor men, then the Law of man can ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tort from thee? if wee ſhould preach vnto you no more Saboth dayes in a yeere, then the Law doth exact at our hands, you would thinke wee ſcarce diſcharged our conſciences. But to the
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:15437:38"/> point; what rent do you meane? that which is in true valew, or that for which, it may be or hath beene lately let? No by no meanes, that were too much; then our Paſtors would bee ſo proud that their owne ſheepe ſhould not be able to rule them; they would tell vs too plainely of our faults, &amp; looke ouer ſeriouſly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our actions. How then? it ſhall be after the old rent, but ſo old, that a new rate of all things are ſince that time in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed fourefold, and our families (by permiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of marriage) are manifold. Is this a fit proportion, when a Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:15437:38"/> ſhall pay but in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion but a fifth of the tithe to that that the countrie labouring man doth pay? When a man ſhall giue a Comiſſarie ſo much towards the poore mans boxe, for a licence to eate fleſh in Lent, as he giues to his Paſtor for feeding of his ſoule all the yeere long? Is that a good proportion? how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer it falls more or leſſe, better or worſe, you will giue no more; and by a fraudulent deuiſe vnder hand, thus you conueigh the matter; we will pay part of the rent by bond, and the reſt by leaſe, ſo wee will ſweare, and ſweare truly, that we
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:15437:39"/> pay no more rent: Or in the ſame leaſe, I will pay part in the name of a fine, For I haue learned a prettie diſtinction be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene Fine and <hi>rent</hi> in that kinde, ſo I will ſwear and ſweare truely that I paid no more rent. And wilt thou ſweare this? oh colluſion worſe then Ieſuitiſme.</p>
                  <p>Beloued, you had bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter equiuocate for all the clothes in your ſhops; for all your goods by ſea &amp; land, then in this caſe. It is Gods cauſe, and <hi>God is not mocked, whatſoeuer a man ſoweth in this kinde he ſhall bee ſure to reape the ſame.</hi> Remember <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nias and Saphirah;</hi> for this
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:15437:39"/> is done not vnto men, but vnto God, <hi>did you ſell your poſſeſſion for ſo much?</hi> yea, <hi>for ſo much,</hi> ſaith <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanias,</hi> and iuſt for ſo much ſaith <hi>Saphirah;</hi> they ſaid ſo, but they did not ſweare ſo; yet you ſee what a harueſt they did reape preſently, by not obeying Gods will; I would to God wee were worthy to moue that high Court of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in this one miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe. If wee haue too much, let them giue vs leſſe; onely let there bee plaine dealing in Gods cauſe; let them not ſuffer men to run their ſoules and conſciences vpon the pikes of periury, vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:15437:40"/> theſe nice equiuoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions which ſhall pierce them through vnto eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall death.</p>
                  <p>I am ſure I haue wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried your patience; but one word more, and I will remooue my finger from this ſore. Shall I tell you what is the cauſe of all this, beſides that roote of all euill, coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe which rootes vp all pietie and dutie, that concernes the purſe? beſide that pride of heart that makes euery one al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt to thinke himſelfe wiſer then his Teacher, and that they are able of themſelues to preſcribe Lawes vnto their owne conſciences; there is one
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:15437:40"/> eſpeciall cauſe of the tranſgreſſion of this my text: The very ſame which was the occaſion that moued the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> to write this text. Doe you know what <hi>Corban</hi> meanes? it is in the ſeuenth of Saint <hi>Markes</hi> Goſpell at the 11. verſe, it is when as voluntarie oblations doe diſpenſe with neceſſarie duties: Bring your of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frings to vs ſay the Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſes, and then for the reſt it is no matter; <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ban,</hi> ſuch Phariſes did bewitch the <hi>Galathians,</hi> againſt whom the Apo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtle writeth this Epiſtle; who as they did with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw them from the
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:15437:41" rendition="simple:additions"/> truth, ſo withall they did withdraw the main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance from their true Teachers. And our A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle may ſeeme by the ſpirit of prophecie to haue directed this wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Epiſtle againſt our Prieſts and Ieſuits, who crie, <hi>Corban</hi> vnto their Diſciples; telling them, that they are their ghoſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fathers; it is no matter for their Miniſters; ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glect them as Hereticall: and I pray God that <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cah,</hi> that is, the Courtier <note place="margin">Iudg. 17. 10.</note> and the Church-robbing Patron haue not taught his Leuite and trencher Chaplaine alſo who ſits at his table and ſerues in his houſe, to ſay <hi>Corban,</hi>
                     <pb n="79" facs="tcp:15437:41"/> that his ſtipendarie pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion which hee begrudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth him out of his bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice is rather a beneuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence then a dutie.</p>
                  <p>Be not offended, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued, becauſe I haue told you the truth, I haue of purpoſe abſtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from any thing that is queſtionable; the truth, as I haue conceiued it, I haue tould you plainly and briefly, &amp; as I haue diſcharged my conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence in this point, ſo I doe humbly and hearti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pray vnto the God of heauen, that al of vs, may both in this, and all the reſt, diſcharge our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences in obeying the truth; that wee may ſo
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:15437:42"/> diſpoſe of our ſelues, as nether the profits nor the pleaſures of this world any way hinder vs from this truth, that wee may place our hearts &amp; ſoules on the certainety and the generalty of the ſame, that <hi>as a man ſoweth ſo ſhall hee alſo reape,</hi> either the ſame in kinde, or in proportion. Whatſoeuer it be, be it good or euill, ſowne to the fleſh or to the ſpirit; be it in pietie, or Charitie; bee it more or leſſe, he ſhall be ſure to reape the ſame; partly in this world, but moſt fully in the world to come. Let vs now deſire of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God our graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Lord for a ſhower of
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:15437:42"/> grace for this that in ſome weake meaſure hath bin ſowed amongſt vs at this time, that it may fructifie and be co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered and receiued into our hearts ſo as Satan do neuer ſteale it away; but that it may take deepe roote in our hearts, and bring foorth fruite to our endleſſe comfort through Ieſus Chriſt our LORD</p>
                  <closer>Amen.</closer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:15437:43"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:15437:43"/>
                  <p>A SERMON PREACHED AT Mercers chapell in LENT 1614.</p>
                  <p>BY ROGER FENTON <hi>D. in Diuinitie.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <figure/>
                  <p>LONDON Printed for <hi>William Aſpley.</hi> 1616.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:15437:44"/>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="sermon">
                  <pb n="85" facs="tcp:15437:44"/>
                  <epigraph>
                     <bibl>CANTIC. 8. 6.</bibl>
                     <q>Set mee as a ſeale on thine heart, and as a ſignet vpon thine arme, for Loue is ſtrong as death, Iealouſie is cruell as the graue.</q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE ſodaine change, of the perſon in this kinde of SCRIPTVRE which is penned Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue-wiſe is the cauſe of
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:15437:45"/> the greater difficultie of it, but for the vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of theſe wordes which now I haue read vnto you, they do con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne the Speaker whoſe words they be, whether the words of the Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grome vnto his ſpouſe, or the wordes of the ſpouſe vnto her Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grome, whether Chriſt ſpeaketh them vnto his Church or the Church of Chriſt vnto him. And it makes little difference whether that Chriſt our Sauiour do exhort vs to ſet him as a ſeale vpon our hearts and to weare him as a ſignet vpon our arme, or whether that the Church do deſire Chriſt
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:15437:45"/> to ſet her as a ſeale vpon his heart or to ſet her as a ſignet vpon his arme, the difference is no more then the counterpane betweene one and the ſame leaſe, for here the ſame things are deliuered vp betweene Chriſt and his Church enterchange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably, ſo hath Almighty God in his wiſedome e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer prouided through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the whole doctrine of Chriſtianity as Saint <hi>Auſtine</hi> noteth, that thoſe places which are of moſt difficulty there is in them the leaſt danger of miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking, and thoſe points that are moſt neceſſarie to be knowne vnto ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion they are moſt plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:15437:46"/> of all other expreſſed in the booke of God. If yee conceiue them to bee the wordes of the Church vnto Chriſt, then they deuide them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues into a petition and a reaſon of the petition, &amp; if you conceiue them to be the words of Chriſt vnto his Church then they diuide themſelues into an exhortation and a motiue, each of them twofold; for the word of this affection of loue ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer vſeth to come ſingle, for hee that loues, loues for to dwell vpon it, for to repeate and to reite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate the petition or the exhortation which is the firſt part, which is expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:15437:46"/> by a ſeale on the hart, and againe by a ſignet placed vpon the arme; the reaſons or the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiues being alſo double it taketh hold of two affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, the affection of loue and feare, the two hands of the ſoule as Saint <hi>Auſtin</hi> calleth them by which the ſoule is pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and mooued to and fro; either vnto good or vnto bad actions. Here is Loue, ſtronge loue, ſtronge as death, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection that will mooue vs: if not, here is feare of Iealouſie that growes cruell, Iealouſie cruell as the graue, if loue will moue vs, wee ſhall bee knit vnto Chriſt, that
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:15437:47"/> way; if not, if feare will moue vs, wee ſhall bee drawne vnto Chriſt that way; and if neither of theſe ſingle will moue vs: if both together will moue vs, here is feare that growes out of loue, &amp; grounded vpon loue; loue is ſtrong as death; but if abuſed ſhe growes iealous, and that Iealou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie growes cruell. But if neither loue nor feare nor both theſe grafted together, will drawe vs, then is our caſe moſt deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate, &amp; this I conceiue to bee the reſolution of the text, &amp; the branches whereof you haue heard in my text, <hi>Set mee as a ſeale on thine heart and as</hi>
                     <pb n="91" facs="tcp:15437:47"/> 
                     <hi>a ſignet vpon thine arme:</hi> that is the petition of the Church; or the euidence of Chriſt his two meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phors, which doe moſt liuely expreſſe and ſet foorth vnto vs. The neere coniunction be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene Chriſt and his Church, in the 22. of <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remie</hi> the 24. verſe, as I liue ſaith the Lord, though <hi>Coniah</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Iehoiakim</hi> king of <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah</hi> were the ſignet of my right arme, that is, as neere to mee as neere poſſiblie could be, yet I would caſt him off; The perſonall vnion of the ſonne of God vnto our nature it is the firſt great myſterie of godlineſſe,
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:15437:48"/> for without controuerſie great is the myſterie of godlineſſe the 1. of <hi>Tim.</hi> the 3. chap. the laſt verſ. God manifeſted in the fleſh. Yet notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding you may be bold to ſay that this vnion wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of <hi>Salomon</hi> doth here ſpeake it is aboue that and a neerer vnion and coniunction vnto vs in two reſpects; firſt that hypoſtaticall vnion, it was the coniunction of God and mans nature in generall, but this comes neerer &amp; doth incorpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate our particular per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons into one bodie with Chriſt. Howſoeuer the other in his owne nature bee great betweene the
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:15437:48"/> things themſelues vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, yet notwithſtanding this is vnto vs more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable becauſe it brings with it a particular appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation to euery one, that wee may ſay and pray with <hi>Dauid</hi> in the 35. <hi>Pſalme</hi> the 3. verſe, <hi>Say vnto my ſoule I am thy ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation,</hi> not onely vnto all in generall but vnto thy ſoule and my ſoule in particular which is more comfortable. Therefore God hee hath for this purpoſe not only ordain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the preaching of the Goſpell in publike to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare the loue of God in Chriſt Ieſus to mankind, in generall; but hee hath alſo inſtituted ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:15437:49"/> which are mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred vnto euery ones perſons in particular; that as Gods loue is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all, ſo he confirmeth the ſame loue to euery one in particular that is capable of the ſame.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iunction which this me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taphor expreſſeth, it ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedeth the other in this, that though Chriſt did take our nature vpon him, and our nature with all humane infirmities, yet hee did take it cleane voide of all ſinne; but in this miſticall vnion be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene Chriſt and his members, though we be full of ſinne and infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties as well in ſoule as
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:15437:49"/> body, yet he vouchſafed to knit vs vnto himſelfe as being one bodie. Ieſus Chriſt ties vs as in an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeparable knot, which v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity is moſt comfortably in the Scripture ſet forth by two Metaphors, both which come ſhort of theſe meraphors in my text. It is expreſſed by the head and the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers; and by man and wife, but <hi>Nero</hi> or ſome Tyrant may chop the head from the members; and death doth make a ſeparation between man and wife; but of this vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſaith the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> I am perſwaded neither death, nor life, principalities, nor pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers,
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:15437:50"/> ſhall be able to ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate vs from Chriſt, and in the 8. of the Epiſtle to the <hi>Bomanes</hi> the 28. alſo we know that all things worke together for the beſt vnto them that loue God, euen to them that are called of his purpoſe. But the two metaphors of my text are more em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaticall; for the heart, it is the fountaine of life, it is the firſt that liueth and the laſt that dieth; and the arme is the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument of power; if Chriſt haue ſet vs as a ſeale vpon his heart, and as a ſignet vpon his arme, let vs ſee what principalities or power, what life or death, is able
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:15437:50"/> to make a ſeparation be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene vs, except he can be ouercome who is om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipotent God himſelfe, this ſignet ſhall neuer bee plucked from his arme; and vnleſſe he can die a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, who is life it ſelfe, the Lord of life, this ſeale which is imprinted in his heart ſhall neuer be blotted out; this ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable coniunction be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene Chriſt and vs, it is here declared in this place, and propounded by way of a petition, whereof we may be bold to make a poſition and ſay indeede that Chriſt hath ſet vs as a ſeale vpon his heart and that he hath worne vs as a ſignet vpon
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:15437:51"/> his arme. For that which was the wiſh the prayer &amp; deſire of the Church, in <hi>Salomons</hi> time when this ſong was ſung, that is now inioyed by the Church of Chriſt; their wiſh is our Article; their prayer our creede; wee doe beleeue it, becauſe Chriſt hath manifeſted it; ſince the Son of God did take vnto him an heart and an arme, that is to ſay a humane ſoule within, and a naturall bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die without, hee hath in that ſoule and body fully granted the petition to the Church, and ſet vs as a ſeale vpon his heart. For were not we deepely imprinted in his heart
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:15437:51"/> when he ſuffered his hart to bee deuided by the point of the ſpeare, when he ſhed out water &amp; his heart bloud in loue vnto vs, when he was in a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner forſaken of his owne Father rather then his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhould forſake vs. That Euangelicall Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> in the 49. cha: ver. 16. ſaith in the perſon of God vnto <hi>Zion, I haue ingrauen thee in the palmes of my hands;</hi> were we not deepely ingrauen in the palme of Chriſts hands when hee ſuffered both hands and feete to bee pierced vpon the croſſe, it was a deep impreſſion; and Chriſt would neuer haue ſuffered it vnleſſe
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:15437:52"/> this ſeale had bin deeply printed in his hands, ſhowing them after his reſurrection this print ſtill, in the 24. of Luke, <hi>Behold my hands and feet.</hi> It is a queſtion amongſt Diuines whether thoſe ſcarres in the hands and in the ſides of our bleſſed Sauiour which remained in his bodie after his death &amp; reſurrection (to the end that hee might ſhew himſelf vnto a few) doe not yet remaine in his glorious body being in heauen; that he may ſhew them at the laſt day of his reſurrection, that they might looke vpon him whom they had pierced; and this is
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:15437:52"/> without all queſtion the impreſſion ſpoken of in this place, remayning ſtill on his hands and heart, and Ieſus Chriſt doth euen weare vs and makes as precious ac<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>count of vs as the ſignet of his right hand; for the ſame affections hee had here on the earth, he hath carried them with the ſame bodie vp into heauen; and as hee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred vs vpon the Croſſe, ſo doth hee not forget vs when he is now in his kingdome. Hee is not like <hi>Pharoahs Butler</hi> that forgat <hi>Ioſeph</hi> (who was ſo kinde to him in priſon) when hee came to his preferment; but
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:15437:53"/> Chriſt hee remembred the petition of the thefe, thou now remembreſt vs becauſe thou art in the ſame paſſion with vs, ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect to the ſame death, but when this paſſion is paſt, when thou co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meſt into thy kingdome, ô God remember me then. So doth Chriſt remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber vs now when hee is come into heauen to the right hand of God; hee remembers vs as hee did remember vs when hee was dying and ſhed his precious blood for vs on the Croſſe. Wherefore did he take humane af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection vpon him, but that hee might expreſſe this loue vnto vs?</p>
                  <pb n="103" facs="tcp:15437:53"/>
                  <p> The affection of loue is noted to be moſt vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in women, as <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> doth expreſſe 2. Sam: 1 26. ſpeaking of Iona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than; <hi>Thy loue to me was wonderfull, paſſing the loue of women.</hi> And becauſe the affections of that ſexe are naturall &amp; ſo ſhould be moſt tender, therefore our Sauiour when hee came to bee incarnated and to take our fleſh vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him, he was <hi>made of a woman</hi> Gal: 4. 4. and yet becauſe ſinne doth natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally harden the heart, and dull the affection, therefore he tooke them from a pure Virgin, and that they might yet bee more tender, he did free
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:15437:54"/> them and purge them from all ſinne: and theſe affections hath he in his bodie taken vp with him into heauen and ſet them at the right hand of God his Father, and therefore I may be bold to ſay hee hath ſet vs as a ſeale vpon his heart, and as a ſignet vpon his arme, and with his ſtretched-out arme he hath mightily defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vs, and preſerued his poore Church from time to time from all enemies.</p>
                  <p>Thus the petition is eaſily heard and granted, therefore I will not ſtand long vpon it; that which happily you are more loth to heare, yet that
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:15437:54"/> which is more needfull for mee to ſpeake, is the dutie reflecting vpon it, if we take that ſenſe, or the very literall ſenſe it ſelfe, that Chriſt doth exhort vs that we ſet him on our hearts as a ſeale, and weare him as a ſignet on our arme. And of this dutie here be many branches notably expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in theſe two meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phors. For firſt there's a <hi>heart,</hi> there we muſt euer begin. It is a maxime in Diuinitie, that which the heart doth not, is not done at all before God: for whatſoeuer is done, is but formally done, it is not effectually done, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe the heart be affected
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:15437:55"/> with it: the heart it is the firſt that liues by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, ſo it is the firſt that muſt liue againe in our regeneration and new birth: It is the firſt that God doth challenge in the firſt Commandment of the firſt Table, <hi>Thou ſhalt haue no other gods be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore me,</hi> that is, in my pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, or before mee in thine owne affection, <hi>but thou ſhalt loue me with all thine heart and with all thy ſoule</hi> &amp;c. It is the laſt Commandment of the ſecond Table, <hi>Thou ſhalt not couet,</hi> in thy heart. God in his Table begins with the heart firſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe in all our actions the firſt thing that God
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:15437:55"/> beholds is the heart: but in the ſecond Table which is for continuall duties amongſt men, it is in the laſt place, becauſe the laſt that a man can ſee, is to ſee into the heart; ſo then to take all ten Commandments to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, the heart you ſee it is the <hi>Alpha</hi> &amp; <hi>Omega</hi> the firſt and the laſt of all, and ſo in truth it is all in all, for giue God the heart and all the reſt will follow; a heart therfore hee doth claime at our hands in this exhortation in the firſt place, and this heart it muſt be wrought like wax that it may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the impreſſion of a ſeale, for ſo ſaith Chriſt
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:15437:56"/> here to his Church, <hi>ſet me as a ſeale vpon thy hart.</hi> You know the matter that is diſpoſed for to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue an impreſſion, it muſt neither be too hard nor too ſoft, for if it bee ouer hard it will not take it, and if ouer fluxible it will not hold it, therfore the heart muſt bee of a good temper to receiue the impreſſion of the ſeale of Chriſt. As a braine if it be too dry it will not be apprehenſiue, and if too moiſt it will not be retentiue, it muſt be a well tempered brain that ſhall receiue both in apprehenſion and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie: So the heart that receiueth Chriſt and his
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:15437:56"/> righteouſnes muſt be of a good temper: ſome hearts are too hard that will take no impreſſion at all, like the hearts of the Cheifetaines among the Iewes, that nothing could mollifie them, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing would moue them, nothing would perſwade them to haue pitty and compaſſion on our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour Chriſt. <hi>Pilat</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe when hee had made furrowes on his backe with ſcourging him and crowned his head with thornes, he brought him out before them, to ſee if they would haue pitty and compaſſion on him to ſay it is enough; but their hearts they were
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:15437:57"/> hardned they would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue no impreſſion at all: On the other ſide the hearts of the people, they were ſoft and vnſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and vnconſtant, rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to cry <hi>Hoſanna</hi> one day, <hi>Bleſſed is hee that commeth in the name of the Lord;</hi> and ſhortly after <hi>Crucifige, Crucifige;</hi> the hearts of men do offend in theſe two extremities, ſomtime they are too hard to receiue any im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, and ſomtimes they are againe too in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſtant they will not hold it, there be as a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine ſpeaketh, not onely Sabbatarians that were heretikes, but Sunday-Chriſtians alſo that hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:15437:57"/> vpon the Sabbath will take ſome impreſſion; ſome certaine qualme of religion haply may come ouer their conſciences, but it is quickly gone againe; they ſerue God vpon the Sabbath, and ſerue themſelues and the Deuill all the weeke af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: they are reſembled vnto that goodly Idoll <hi>Dagon</hi> in the 5. chap: of the 1. booke of <hi>Samuel</hi> the 4. verſe, who ſo long as he ſtood in his place in the temple was a good<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly Idol to looke vpon, but the next morning when they came they found his hands and his head at the threſhold of his temple, ſo as the text
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:15437:58"/> ſaith, <hi>there was nothing left but the very ſtumpe of an Idol;</hi> ſo is it with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of vs who comming into the houſe of God to heare a Sermon, and it may be with great ſhew of deuotion alſo to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the Sacrament, but at the Church do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e there lies their hands and affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, nothing remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth but a very ſtumpe of religion, they haue neither hands to doe a good deed, nor happily tongues to ſpeake a good word all the weeke after; theſe be Sabbath day Chriſtians. But if we will fruitfully receiue the ingraffed word of Chriſt which is able to
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:15437:58"/> ſaue our ſoules, as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſpeaketh Iam: 1<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 21 We muſt haue a heart fit to receiue and retaine that his impreſſion; <hi>ſet me</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>as a ſeale vpon thy heart,</hi> the image of Chriſt and the ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of Chriſt muſt be both vpon our hearts, our Sauiour Chriſt ſaith in the 17 of Mathew, when they brought him a peece of money, <hi>Whoſe image and ſuperſcription is this, they ſaid it was Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſars, why then giue vnto Caeſar that which is Caeſars and giue vnto God that which is Gods:</hi> the image that muſt bee vpon our hand, it muſt not be the marke of the beaſt Apoc.
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:15437:59"/> 13. 16. in token that wee ſubſcribe to the doctrine of Antichriſt, but it muſt be the image of Chriſt, and the ſuperſcription written about it muſt be the goſpell of Chriſt. If in our liues and conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſations we conforme our ſelues to the image of Chriſt in righteouſneſſe and true holineſſe Epheſ. 4. 24. walking not after the fleſh but after the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit Rom: 8. 1. and if only to the goſpell of Chriſt which is his true ſtampe and ſuperſcription; then we are Chriſts<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> For Chriſt will make a-like diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of men at the laſt day, as he did of the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney-coines amongſt the
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:15437:59"/> Iewes; hee looks vpon the heart and tries the reines, and will then aske <hi>Whoſe ſuperſcription haue yee on your hearts,</hi> which muſt either be the print of Chriſt, or the Deuills ſtampe, thoſe which are Chriſts ſhall be giuen to him, and that which is the Deuils ſhall bee ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred to him, to bee tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented for euer. It be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houeth vs therefore to looke vnto this maine point aboue all the reſt, that we receiue the right ſtampe of our Sauiour Chriſt, and be obedient vnto the ſuperſcription of his goſpell; and then ſhall wee be ſure to giue vnto him a hand and a
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:15437:60"/> heart, but thats not all, we muſt haue an arme of prompt execution, to an heart of ſincere religion. You know that the heart is the ſeate of affection, and the hand it is the in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtrument of action, and if Chriſt be imprinted in our affections, then cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly wee will ſhew Chriſt in our actions; They be the two parts of the ſacred Law of God.</p>
                  <p>The firſt table as our Sauiour Chriſt teacheth<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> it was thus, thou ſhould<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> loue the Lord thy God with all thine heart, there is the ſeale on the heart; and with all thy ſtrength, there is the ſeale on the arme, for that is the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:15437:60" rendition="simple:additions"/> of ſtrength. Againe, an heart with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out an arme, you know, it is impotent, it would faine, but cannot: and an arme without an hart is lame and maimed, therfore both theſe muſt goe together, wee muſt haue an heart to receiue the impreſſion of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian religion, and wee muſt haue an arme alſo to defend it. Religion muſt haue a ſoule and a body; againe, the loue that is in the heart is ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret to our ſelues, ſo is all affection; the ſeale vpon the heart is within, but the ſeale vpon the arme is apparant to the world, ſo that if we weare Chriſt
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:15437:61"/> in our hearts inwardly, certainely wee will ſhew him in our actions out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly, as thou weareſt Chriſt vpon the heart, that is, as a priuy ſeale betweene God and thee; but if thou weareſt Chriſt as a ſignet on the arme, that is, as the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique great ſeale before the world. Secondly, how muſt we weare him on the arme? as a ſignet, ſaith the Text, that is, as an ornament; ſo farre we muſt bee from being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed of the Goſpell of Chriſt, that we muſt glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in it, and ſay with the Apoſtle, <hi>God forbid that I ſhould glorie in any thing but in the croſſe of Chriſt;</hi>
                     <pb n="119" facs="tcp:15437:61"/> Galat. 6. 14. As the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Ieremy</hi> ſaith, <hi>Can a maide forget her orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, or a bride her attire? yet my people haue forgot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten me dayes without num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, ſaith the Lord.</hi> God would haue vs to make account of him, as of that which we moſt eſteeme, as an ornament on thine arme. But what orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are ſignets? a ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net is that which makes an impreſſion on ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thing, as you vſe to weare your rings on your thumbs, not onely for ornament, but ro ſeale letters withall: ſo a ſignet was worne on the arme, to make an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion and ſeale, in like
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:15437:62"/> manner would Chriſt be worne of Chriſtians, not onely to reioyce and glory in him publikely, and by an expreſſion of him in their outward ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; but ſo to ſet him out, as they make an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of their religion &amp; of Chriſt in the hearts of others. In the 12. of Dan. the 3. thoſe that are wiſe ſhall ſhine as the brightneſſe of the firma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and they that turn many to righteouſneſſe ſhall ſhine as the ſtarres in the firmament, for as the ſtarres are the brigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt parts of their orbes, ſo thoſe that are truely wiſe, not to themſelues onely, carrying the light
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:15437:62"/> of their knowledge reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uedly in their own harts, but ſo ſhew it and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate it, as that they conuert others: they ſhall ſhine in an higher degree of glory in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, then others, and this is a point that doth eſpecially concern thoſe that are in any place of authority whatſoeuer, according to that talent of gouernment that God hath entruſted them withall and tied as a bracelet about their armes, that they ſhould in their Chriſtian and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious carriage, make an impreſſion of vertue and deuotion in thoſe that are vnder them. And this is
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:15437:63"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="121" facs="tcp:15437:63"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="122" facs="tcp:15437:64"/> to weare Chriſt, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as an ornament to themſelues, but as a ſeale to imprint him in others. It is a point that the ſchoole Diuines haue determined vpon good and probable ground, that as thoſe who are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious in their places, and haue power to doe much good in this world they ſhall ſhine more glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly in heauen; ſo like wiſe, they that are in place of authoritie, and by their bad examples draw others from God, they ſhall be caſt as deep into hell; <hi>Potentes poten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter tormenta patientur;</hi> mighty men ſhall bee mightily puniſhed, Wiſd.
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:15437:64"/> 6. 5. 8. therefore it is ſaid <note place="margin">Eſ. 30. 33.</note> that <hi>Tophet</hi> is prepared for great perſonages that are wicked ones, and by their euil examples draw multitudes after them. What moued the rich glutton in hel to become ſolicitor for his brethren at home that they ſhould conuert and repent, was it any charitie or loue towards them? No his conſcience told him that he had ſhewed them bad examples while he liued, and if they were damned his torment ſhould bee the greater for it. This is the exhortation that Chriſt makes to his Church that wee would ſet him as a ſeale vpon
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:15437:65"/> our hearts, and ſet him as a ſignet on our arme.</p>
                  <p>The motiues to ſtirre vs vp to this dutie follow, for <hi>loue is ſtrong as death and ielouſie cruell as the graue.</hi> But whoſe loue and whoſe ielouſie doth my text here ſpeake of? of the ielouſie of the Church vnto Chriſt, or of CHRIST vnto the Church? It is the ielou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie of Chriſt without queſtion; for God he is ielous of vs, but we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not bee ielous of God: and to ſpeake after the manner of men, we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue ielouſie (if it bee true and vnfained) to be nothing elſe but an affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of loue, tending
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:15437:65"/> vnto hatred vpon ſuſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that loue is abuſed: Now when wee doe aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribe any humane affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction vnto God, we muſt ſeparate from it all im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfections whatſoeuer; if there be a ielouſie not grounded in loue it is faultie; or if it be a ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie without cauſe it is blame worthy: neither of theſe faults are in the ielouſie that we aſcribe vnto GOD, and vnto CHRIST: hee is a ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous God, but his ielou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie proceeds of loue, though it tend vnto hate vpon ſuſpition that loue is abuſed; and not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out cauſe: ſo God may be ielous of vs, but wee
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:15437:66"/> cannot be ielous of God; the reaſon is, becauſe he that is ielous is ielous of a partner in loue. I would to God (ſaith <hi>S. Paul</hi> to <hi>Agrippa,</hi> Act. 26. 29.) I would that all that heare me this day were both almoſt, and altogether ſuch as I am. <hi>S. Paul</hi> cares not how many partners hee hath in the loue of Chriſt; the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the difference is that the loue of God to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards vs is infinite; but our loue vnto Chriſt it is ſo ſtraight and ſo narrow, that if ſo be he haue any partners with him, it is to be feared he ſhall not haue his due, ſo that hee hath cauſe to be ielous.
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:15437:66"/> Wherefore without all queſtion wee muſt take this motiue to be ſpoken of Chriſt and of his ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie. <hi>Loue is ſtrong as death, Ielouſie is cruell as the graue,</hi> to ſhew the ſtrength of Chriſts loue vnto vs, the Holy Ghoſt hath made a fit compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon. For what is ſtron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger than death that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoureth all? Surely the loue of Chriſt vnto man. Marke then what is the generall effect of death; yee know it is the ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the ſoule and the body; taking the ſoule out of the body, and leauing it wan, pale and gaſtly. And that is likewiſe the effect of the
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:15437:67"/> extremitie of loue; eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially of Chriſts loue to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards vs. For this pure, chaſt and diuine loue wherewith Chriſt loued vs, it made him to emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie himſelf that he might fill vs; to go out of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe that he might dwell in vs; to die once in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe that wee might liue for euermore.</p>
                  <p>Wherein did death euer ſhew his greateſt power? Verily in ſeaſing vpon the Sonne of God our Sauiour himſelfe, then was ſhowne the greateſt power that euer death exerciſed. Yet let me tell you, herein the loue of Chriſt was farre ſtronger than death.
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:15437:67"/> Death ſeazed on Chriſt when hee was become man vpon the earth, but the loue of Chriſt to vs, pulled him out of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, when hee was in the boſome of his Father; and humbled him and made him ſo weake, that hee might become a fit Redeemer for vs. What ailed thee thou great ſtrong <hi>Sampſon</hi> of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, ſaith <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> thou that bindeſt Kings in chaines, what meanes this, ſurely it was the loue of Chriſt to our tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherous nature, that delt ſo vntruly and ſo falſly with him, that pulled this <hi>Sampſon</hi> out of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, and made him as
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:15437:68"/> weake as one of vs. To ſpeake properly, when death did ſeaze on chriſt in his weaknes, it was not the power of death, but the power of loue Chriſt tels vs ſo plainly in the 10. of Iohn the 18 verſ: <hi>I lay downe my life, no man taketh it from me.</hi> So then take death at the ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, ſtill the loue of Chriſt vnto vs is ſtronger than death. Wee haue heard ſufficiently of the loue of Chriſt vnto vs, if this will not draw from vs loue againe vnto Chriſt, what will? True loue is of the nature of a Loade-ſtone it drawes loue vnto it, <hi>Magnes amoris amor;</hi> but ſuch is our ingratitude,
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:15437:68"/> though we loue to heare of the loue of Chriſt, yet wee care not to ſhew our loue to him againe. This vnthankfulnes of vs in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratefull wretches is the the cauſe that wee are euer ſo loth to be drawn vnto him. <hi>Dauid</hi> in the 118. Pſalme the 27. verſ. ſpeaking of the ſacrifice that was offred; when he reckons vp the loue of God towards vs, he ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth ſodenly in regard of our retribution of loue backe to him againe, binde the ſacrifice with cords, yea euen to the hornes of the Altar. It is a ſaying amongſt the Hebrewes, that the beaſts that were offered in ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:15437:69"/> they were the ſtrug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingſt <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Procul ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tenſum pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tula<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tit h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ſtia funem. Juven: Satyr.</hi> 12.</note> beaſts of all the reſt, ſuch is the nature of vs vnthankfull beaſts, when wee ſhould loue God againe, we are rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier for to runne away from him, wee muſt bee tyed to the Altar with cords, to draw from vs loue or feare. Though it bee true that forced loue is no loue; <hi>Non ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor quebis amari.</hi> His loue is ſtrong as death, but if we abuſe his loue by our vnthankfulneſſe, then marke what followes, out of his loue, hee growes ielous, and that ielouſie growes cruell, cruel euen as the graue. Ielouſie (ſaith <hi>Salomon)</hi> it is the
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:15437:69"/> raging of a man, it will not be pacified, Prou: 6. 34, 35. Remember the Law and the ſacrifice that was appointed for ielous perſons in the 5. of Num: the 15. verſe, there was neither oyle to make it gracious, nor incenſe to giue place of atonement or reconciliation. For intire loue it will not be adulterated, nor yet ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer it ſelfe to be wronged: ſuch is the nature of mans ielouſie. Our God he is a ielous God, and our bleſſed Sauiour out of the vehemencie of his loue, he is a louing Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our and ielous too; but the ground of this ielou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie it is loue, and if his
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:15437:70"/> loue be abuſed, it tends vnto hate vpon iuſt ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pition of a iuſt cauſe. Then to ſumme vp all in a word; it is the prima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie nature of our good God &amp; bleſſed Sauiour to bee moſt louing and gracious vnto vs; ſo is it the nature of that loue if there bee iuſt cauſe to grow ielous, and it is the nature of that ielouſie to be cruell, cruell as the graue, if ſo be before the graue we do not appeaſe it, and be reconciled to our husband Chriſt by true repentance. For we may aſſure our ſelues, that if our Sauior Chriſt finde any impreſſion in the heart, deeper than
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:15437:70"/> this ſet vpon it, or any ornament aboue true re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion &amp; faith in Chriſt; hee will preſently grow ielous, and that ielouſie will grow cruell. In the 22 of Geneſis, when as <hi>Abraham</hi> ſeemed for to bee fond of his ſonne <hi>Iſaack,</hi> God tryeth <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> what he would doe for his ſake: yea he tries him whether hee loued him truly and indeed, or no: Therefore, ſaith he to <hi>Abraham,</hi> go and take thy ſonne, thy onely ſon <hi>Iſaack,</hi> and offer him vp for a ſacrifice: <hi>Abraham</hi> ſhowes there though he loued his ſonne <hi>Iſaack</hi> very dearely and tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, yet notwithſtanding,
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:15437:71"/> it was not to be compar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with his loue to God.</p>
                  <p>In the Decalogue of the Law, God hee is ſo iealous he wil not ſet any creature in the ſame ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of the Law with him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, there ſhal ſtand nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Father nor Mother, King nor <hi>Caeſar,</hi> Saint nor Angell; none in the ſame table with God: he is a iealous God if there be cauſe. And Beloued, there is none of vs but wee haue giuen him iuſt cauſe many times, and therefore he muſt needes be iealous: but yet his ielouſie is not cruell, it is not cruell as the graue, if ſo be that before hand in time we doe preuent this
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:15437:71"/> wrath and cruelty; if ſo be we humble our ſelues and be reconciled vnto God by true repentance, God is a ielous God and viſits the ſinnes of the fathers vpon the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren.</p>
                  <p>We haue often pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoked our Husband-Chriſt to ielouſie; Oh that now we would pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent his wrath while there is time of grace; now is there time of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation if ſo be wee will labour and ſeeke for it, if we will humble our ſelues by prayer and hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility, by faſting and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing our faults vnto God and vnto our bleſſed Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:15437:72"/> with teares, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoluing neuer to giue him the like cauſe again; and as at all times this dutie is ſeaſonable, ſo eſpecially at theſe times when as it ſhould be ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall, to the end that the more hearts meete in this diſpoſition, it may be ſo much the more ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable a ſacrifice to God. Prayer and Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militie is required of vs at all times before God; praier and faſting is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired of vs vpon occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; for euery mans particular ſinnes preſent to God and himſelfe is a ſufficient occaſion of pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate prayer and faſting; but publike calamitie is
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:15437:72"/> an occaſion of publike faſtings.</p>
                  <p>There be (as a Father calls them when he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaines of the time) cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine ſinnes of Church and Common-wealth, which cannot bee impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to particular perſons, when ſinne is growne ſo common and generall that it is not in the power of any perſon or perſons to reforme the ſame; The remedie againſt ſuch an Epidemicall diſeaſe, is the publicke ſupplicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Church, when we muſter vp our praiers as an armie, not onely to beſeech God, but to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiege him too, when we doe all agree and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:15437:73"/> together by repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance and true humiliati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to preuent the wrath of God vpon Church &amp; common-wealth, which we haue deſerued; pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent I ſay that, that ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie doe not turne into wrath; for if it doe, and be not preuented, it will burne into the very bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome of hel <hi>Deut.</hi> 32. 22. Therefore let vs humble our ſelues before almigh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tie God, and intreat his glorious Maieſtie that notwithſtanding our pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate ſinnes, wee may be ſet as a ſeale vpon his heart ſo deepely imprin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted that neither height nor depth, nor principa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities nor powers be able
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:15437:73"/> to ſeparate vs from him, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 38. And that we may bee ſtill as a ſignet vpon that arme that hath defended this Church and common-wealth ſo long. That his righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe may be imprin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in our hearts, and his glorie an ornament to vs, and his word pretious among vs, which we beg for his owne ſake that gaue himſelfe for vs, that wee may lay aſide all in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratitude and bee truely thankefull vnto him through Ieſus Chriſt our Sauiour, to whom with the Father and the holy Ghoſt be all honour &amp; glory for euer</p>
                  <closer>Amen.</closer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:15437:74"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:15437:74"/>
                  <p>A SERMON PREACHED AT the Funerall of <hi>Mr</hi>. <hi>Iohn St<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>kele</hi> Citizen and Machant-Taylor of LONDON at S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Steuens in <hi>Walbrooke</hi> 1613.</p>
                  <p>BY ROGER FENTON <hi>D. in Diuinitie.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <figure/>
                  <p>LONDON Printed for <hi>William Aſpley.</hi> 1616.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="sermon">
                  <pb facs="tcp:15437:75"/>
                  <pb n="145" facs="tcp:15437:75"/>
                  <epigraph>
                     <bibl>IOB. 6. 10.</bibl>
                     <q>Then ſhall I yet haue comfort though I burne with ſorrow, let him not ſpare becauſe I haue not denied the words of the holy one.</q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle S. <hi>Paul</hi> the 4. chapt. of the 2. Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle to <hi>Timoth.</hi> at the 2.
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:15437:76"/> verſe, <hi>preach the word, bee inſtant in ſeaſon and out of ſeaſon;</hi> I vnderſtand thus that we ſhould not onely keep our ordinary courſe as <hi>Moſes</hi> was preached in the Synagogue euery Sabboth day, but that we ſhould take all fit occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to teach and inſtruct Gods people though at extraordinarie times as it were out of ſeaſon, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the which the occaſion of this our meeting is one, and as I take it none of the leaſt, for the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> chapt: 57. and the 1. v: maketh it a matter of iuſt reproofe when righteous and mercifull men are taken away from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:15437:76"/> vs and no man doth conſider it, &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is fit that wee be put in minde of it. Wee haue both a righteous and a mercifull man ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from amongſt vs: Therefore haue wee iuſt occaſion to take it into conſideration, as the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion then doth fit vs: ſo that wee alſo might fit the occaſion. I haue made choyſe of a righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and mercifull man in his ſickneſſe, for hee was an vpright and a iuſt man; one that feared God and eſchewed euill, by Gods owne teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie in the ſecond chapt: and the third verſe who deliuered the words that
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:15437:77"/> now I haue read vnto you. For <hi>Iob</hi> was wearied &amp; ſpent with a grieuous and tedious ſickeneſſe in ſo much as he complains in the 7. chap: at the third verſe that hee had for an inheritance the monethes of vanitie and painefull nights were ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed vnto him. Theſe be the words of <hi>Iob,</hi> and it was the very caſe of this our brother now de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted. Monthe after monthe was he tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and yet ſtill put vs in hope of his recouerie but all in vaine, they were as <hi>Iob</hi> termes them <hi>monthes of vanitie,</hi> and painefull nights were appointed vnto him. wherupon the
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:15437:77"/> holy man <hi>Iob</hi> expreſſeth a longing deſire hee had in the premiſes, and the reaſon of this his deſire in the words of my text, Oh that I might haue the thing I deſire and that God would grant me that which I long for, what was that? ſure no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe but that hee might depart out of this world which he hath ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed by three phraſes, in the verſe immediately before my text, that God would deſtroy him, that he would let his hand go and that hee would cut him off. The firſt is a phraſe according to the words directly, becauſe in the ſight of the world
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:15437:78"/> outwardly the righteous may ſeeme to periſh and bee deſtroyed. But the ſecond phraſe is more diuine, that God would let his hand go, as if with one hand, his heauie hand of ſickneſſe, he had beate him downe, and yet notwithſtanding hee had holden him vp; and with the other hand ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported him, now he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires that God would take away that ſuporting hand that he might die, me thinkes he ſpeakes of almighty God as if hee were a kinde of Nurſe that vſeth when men are drawing on towardes death to lift them vp, for if they take away the pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:15437:78"/> preſently they giue vp the Ghoſt: ſo <hi>Iob</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires God that hee would but take away the other hand, that he might de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part out of this world: &amp; becauſe his ordinarie glaſſe was not yet runne, hee might liue many yeeres by the courſe of nature, hee addes a third phraſe that God would cut him off. But <hi>Iob</hi> liu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed much longer after hee had this ſickeneſſe as you may ſee in the laſt chapt. the 16 verſe. And this our Brother depart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the courſe of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture might haue liued much longer if it had pleaſed God. Now the reaſon of this his longing
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:15437:79"/> deſire is deliuered in this my text in three points. Firſt, in his faith and his full expectation of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort after this life in theſe words, <hi>then ſhall I yet haue comfort.</hi> In the ſecond place there is inſerted a parentheſis, which ſets downe the encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of that faith, a god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly magnanimitie and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution; though I burne with ſorrow, let him not ſpare. And thirdly and laſtly here is both the ground of that reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and the onely touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone of his faith, in that his conſcience tells him hee hath not denied the words of the holy one. Of theſe three firſt, and
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:15437:79"/> then of the occaſion to which they are fitted, &amp; of both briefly. <hi>For then ſhall I yet haue comfort though I burne with ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, let him not ſpare be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I haue not denied the words of the holy one.</hi> For the firſt death is terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to nature, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is called the King of feare <hi>Iob.</hi> 18. 14. moſt terrible yet notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding it is but as a cloude, and hee that hath an Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gles eye of faith to looke through the cloude hee may diſcerne that glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous comfortable light, and ſuch an Eagle was the ſeruant of God <hi>Iob;</hi> for being inuironed with ſo many miſeries, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities,
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:15437:80"/> as he was at this time, yet notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing hee doth pierce through the cloude by the eyes of faith, eſpying his euerlaſting conſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. When our Sauiour Chriſt is deſcribed that hee ſhall appeare in the cloudes in the laſt day, it pleaſed him to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare himſelfe to a ſlaine beaſt; for indeed he was the lambe of God ſlaine from the beginning: therefore <hi>Luke</hi> the 17. and the laſt verſe, hee ſaith, <hi>Whereſoeuer the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die is thither will all the Eagles reſort,</hi> nay ſuch is the ſagacity of that crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture as we read, that by the reſort of Eagles in
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:15437:80"/> 
                     <hi>Africa</hi> the Inhabitants foreſee their ſhould bee warre and bloud-ſhedde in that place: and ſuch an Eagle was <hi>Iob:</hi> who liu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo many hundred yeeres before the incar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation foreſawe his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer, chap. the 19. 25. verſe 27. <hi>I know that my Redeemer liueth, a vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Redeemer;</hi> and ſo <hi>Abraham</hi> ſawe Chriſts daies <hi>Iohn</hi> the 8. By this faith did <hi>Iob</hi> receiue comfort beyond the cloude of death. And <hi>Salomon</hi> deſcribeth our Sauiour Chriſt in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond of the Canticles the 9. verſe, that he ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth behinde the Wall, and looketh through a
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:15437:81"/> grate, aluding to the manner of Nurſes, and Mothers that runne be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinde a wall that their children may ſeek them with a greater deſire, ſo doth God in ſickeneſſe he goes behinde the wall and if we haue an eye to ſpie him through the grate there is our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, as that was <hi>Simeons</hi> ground <hi>Lord now letteſt thou thy ſeruant depart in peace, for mine eies haue ſeene their ſaluation,</hi> after he had gotten Chriſt in his armes, that hee had ſeene his ſaluation, hee thought he was in priſon till he departed, and the word ſignifieth for to be looſed out of priſonne
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:15437:81"/> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, and you know that it was that S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaketh <hi>I deſire to bee diſſolued</hi> becauſe hee would bee with Chriſt. No maruell if <hi>Iob</hi> when hee diſcerned this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort deſired to bee taken out of the world, this eie of faith of his, begets a godly magnanimitie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoluing with all patience to vndergoe and not doubting to ouercome whatſoeuer is or can poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiblie bee laid vpon him, heres the phraiſe and a gradation <hi>though I burne with ſorrow, though mine ague bee neuer ſo terrible, the fit neuer ſo fearefull, my miſeries neuer ſo many:</hi> nay as hee ſaith further in the
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:15437:82"/> 13. chap. the 15. verſe, <hi>Though he kill me yet will I truſt in him,</hi> the word in the originall for ſorrow is taken from the root <hi>chus,</hi> that ſignifies the ſorrow of a woman in trauell that cries to God in her paine: ſuch paines will compell a man for to pray, and to pray vnto God moſt earneſtly: it ſeemes by the Prophet that a woman in trauell will crie out vnto God though ſhee ſildome thinke of him at other times; if euer ſhe be in a good minde it is then: and ſuch were the paines that <hi>Iob</hi> was in at this time, <hi>though I burne with ſorrow,</hi> it was a conflict
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:15437:82"/> and a great conflict that <hi>Iob</hi> was now in, and hee wreſtles as it were with <hi>Iacob:</hi> and though ſome ſpeeches of impatience paſſe from <hi>Iob,</hi> yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding hee reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers himſelfe and in the end his hope &amp; patience was crowned, <hi>though I burne with ſorrow, nay let him not ſpare;</hi> Let almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty God lay as much vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on me as it pleaſeth him, ſo that I may at the laſt inherit that which is my hope and comfort. Mee thinkes hee ſpeaketh as though hee would chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge almighty God for theſe temporall afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to doe his worſt, ſo hee might take him out
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:15437:83"/> of the world. I haue ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued three ſtrange phraiſes in Scripture, which doe amplifie that power of faith that pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of prayer and that power of patience, which it pleaſeth God to giue his Saints: he ſpeakes of faith in the 92. Pſalme at the 9. verſe, as if a faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full man were able to point Almighty God to a thing to come. So the Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> ſpeaketh of faith, <hi>Lo thine enemies ſhall periſh,</hi> as if faith did apprehend it ſo clearely, that it pointed God to it, a ſtrange phraſe. And ye know of prayer in the 32. of <hi>Exod.</hi> the 10. verſ. hee ſpeaketh of praier as
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:15437:83"/> though prayer were able to binde the hands of Almighty God; <hi>Let mee alone that my wrath may waxe hot againſt them:</hi> and ſo in this place, the holy Ghoſt ſpeaketh as though the holy man in miſerie would leaue Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God to doe his worſt, <hi>though I burne with ſorrow.</hi> Laſtly the ground of this magnanimitie &amp; the onely touchſtone of this faith of <hi>Iob,</hi> that his conſcience teſtified vnto him that hee had not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied the wordes of the holy Ghoſt: What are thoſe wordes of the holy Ghoſt, and what it is to denie them, bee the two points. By the words of
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:15437:84"/> the holy one in this place conſidering the time wherein <hi>Iob</hi> liued, which is ſuppoſed for to be in the time of nature, I doe not onely vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand thoſe edicts of na<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture which the Apoſtle ſpeaketh of in the 2. to the <hi>Rom.</hi> the 15. verſe, the effect of the morall law, written in their hearts. I meane thoſe common rules of hone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie which wee haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued by the light of nature and reaſon, the heauens declare the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of God as in the 19. Pſalme: I ſay I doe not onely vnderſtand by the words of the holy one in this place that light of
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:15437:84"/> nature but thoſe Reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations alſo by which God reuealed himſelfe more eſpecially to the very Saints of God: and my reaſon is becauſe hee giues God the name of the holy one in this place, for wee know the nature of holineſſe is to ſeparate a thing from that which is common; therefore hee doth not meane in this place, the words of God onely as God is the God of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, but as he is the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour of grace, and as he hath reuealed vnto mee his will by reuelation from God, and ſo is God promiſed vnto his ſaints. Secondly not to denie
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:15437:85"/> theſe words, it is firſt to belieue, to acknowledge, and to profeſſe the ſame; not to denie the power of them in their liues and conuerſations; no not to denie them in that extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity wherein <hi>Iob</hi> now lies. Theſe three I take to containe the full ſenſe of theſe words. For it is not ſufficient by the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiticall Law (whoſe ground is morall) to chew the cudde; but alſo to deuide the hoofe: our feete muſt bee cleane as well as our mouthes; though our lips be neuer ſo holy yet notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding if our waies be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleane wee are as abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable vnto almighty
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:15437:85"/> God as thoſe that haue all vncleane. All is one to the beaſt in the 13. of the <hi>Reuelat.</hi> the 16. whether we haue his marke in the forehead or in the right hand, all is one to Satan; many there be that haue very ſmothe foreheads, and carrie a goodly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of religion, yet notwithſtanding their hands are full of iniquity. <hi>Iob</hi> was as well in life and profeſſion, an vpright &amp; iuſt man, one that feared God and eſchewed euill, an vpright man, firſt as God ſaith of him; a iuſt man towards others in diſtributing vertues; and all this out of conſcience and religion, one that
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:15437:86"/> feared God, and though as the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>euill is alwaies with mee,</hi> yet he laboureth to eſchew e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill, ſo that hee denied not the power of that he profeſſed, he performed the power of the word of God in life and conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, and that not only in proſperitie but in his extremity, in ſickeneſſe and miſerie. It is an eaſie matter not to denie the word of God ſo long as the Lord pleaſeth vs in proſperity, but <hi>Iob</hi> would ſay the Lord hath giuen and the Lord hath taken, yet notwithſtanding bleſſed bee the name of the Lord: ſo wee ſee for the clearenes of his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:15437:86"/> in the 6. chapter the 25. ver. how he chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenges his accuſers, <hi>Can any of you iuſtly accuſe me?</hi> this cleare conſcience wrought in him true ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnanimitie, and it is that makes a man ſtrong as a Lyon, as <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith. As Chriſt is ſaid to ſleepe in the ſhippe in the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt, ſo this is the onely pillow whereon a man muſt reſt, when his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience tells him hee is vpright, though through infirmitie yet hee hath done his poore indeauor <hi>to keepe the wordes of the holy one,</hi> &amp; indeed with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out this cleare conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence let neuer any man preſume of faith, for it is
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:15437:87"/> but a counterfet faith, the wordes of the holy one being firſt ſowne as wee ſee in the heart, that ſeed knit vnto the roote of faith, that roote brings out a tree of Charitie, that tree beares the fruite of good workes, ſo as it is true indeed, we are our ſelues iuſtified before God onely by faith, but our faith is iuſtified to our owne conſcience by charity, and our charitie muſt bee iuſtified before the world by our fruites of charity, and by our godly liues and conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſations. Faith it is an il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumination, it is hard to diſtinguiſh betweene the illumination of the true
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:15437:87"/> ſpirit, and the illuſion of the falſe, therefore it hath pleaſed Almightie God with that heauenly faith to ioyne another vertue of Charitie, that a mans owne conſcience may teſtifie whether his faith be counterfet or no, and becauſe the world can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſee into the heart, therefore that Charitie muſt bee iuſtified by workes, and a good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience ioynes all theſe together, this is the ground of the reſolution of that holy man <hi>Iob,</hi> wherfore he doth deſire to be out of this world You haue heard briefly the commendable miſe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rie of this holy man of
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:15437:88"/> God <hi>Iob:</hi> which as you ſee doth remaine vpon record, not ſo much for his commendations as for our inſtruction; yet for both. Shall I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend beloued this our Brother (here departed) vnto you? he hears it not, his friends deſire it not, I haue not receiued any information concerning him of any, becauſe hee affected it not, what then, a mans name is like his ſhadow the faſter hee runnes away the faſter it followes: the memoriall of the righteous ſhall bee bleſſed, reputed hee was for an vpright and iuſt man in all his dealings, let me vſe the plaine dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:15437:88"/> of the world, I like the phraſe well, hee was an honeſt man, which ciuill honeſty did grow out of conſcience and the feare of God in him: for that is the holy ſalt that muſt ſeaſon all; without which there is no ſacrifice that can bee acceptable vnto him. In religion he was not facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous; if he had had occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to ſpeake of any that were of other opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, if hee conceiued them to be honeſt men he would ſpeake of them ſo charitably as if he did euer remember the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles rule the 3. to the <hi>Philip.</hi> the 15 verſe, thoſe that are perfect be thus
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:15437:89"/> minded and thoſe that are otherwiſe minded God ſhall reueale it vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee alſo. The marke of Ieſus Chriſt I make no queſtion was in his hand as well as in his forehead, his workes were anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to his profeſſion. In his owne familie I haue obſerued that he was nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a ſheepe nor a Lyon but a painefull and a watchfull Shepheard la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring by all meanes &amp; diligence to bring his ſeruants to good; to worke in their thoughts true religion; to examine and catechiſe them; ſuch a comfortable Guide both for ſoule and body that I thinke hee might
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:15437:89"/> haue giuen example in that kinde to the beſt. To his friends and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance moſt louing, kinde, and true hearted, I dare ſay they that had occaſion to trie him would teſtifie no leſſe. In this Pariſh hee hath not beene of many yeeres growth, and ſo ſcarce in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corporated, but a man might eaſily perceue him to be both of that Spirit if the cauſe did require, and withall of that wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome to temper his Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, as I may iuſtly ſay we haue loſt a worthy member in the Church of Chriſt: hee was a true liuing ſtone manifeſting his liuely faith, as by his
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:15437:90"/> religious conuerſation in generall, ſo by his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardneſſe in any good worke whatſoeuer, and hee would doe it in that faſhion as the left hand ſhould not know what the right hand did, his heart delighted in the word of God, and hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the ſame, hee did flouriſh in the houſe of our God; his wife and family, friends and kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, neighbours and acquaintance of the place wherein hee did moſt reſide I ſuppoſe can teſtifie more then I ſay, grounded hee was in a true Chriſtian faith, and had learned <hi>Iobs</hi> grace of <hi>Dominus abſtulit:</hi> he was
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:15437:90"/> a true Eagle hee looked through a thicke cloude of a long and tedious ſickneſſe vnto the happy iſſue and end of all, du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring which time of ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe hee ſhewed ſuch a Chriſtian reſolution that when many had thought hee himſelfe had ſtood moſt in neede of com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fort, then was hee moſt comfortable vnto o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; I euer found him like himſelfe from the beginning of his ſicknes to the end: <hi>hee burned in ſorrow;</hi> God loued him and yet ſpared him not, and now no doubt hee doth reſt in God, bleſſed be the name of God, for that, and let vs deſire the
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:15437:91"/> Lord ſo to bleſſe vs with his ſpirit of grace, that as we profeſſe the words of the holy one, ſo wee may neuer deny the power thereof, but ſo walke according to the ſame, that God may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue glorie, and wee eternall comfort in Ieſus Chriſt,</p>
                  <closer>Amen.</closer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:15437:91"/>
                  <p>A SERMON PREACHED AT the Funerall of <hi>Mr</hi>. <hi>Iohn Newman</hi> Citizen and Grocer of LONDON, at S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Steuens in <hi>Walbrooke.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>BY ROGER FENTON <hi>D. in Diuinitie.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <figure/>
                  <p>LONDON Printed for <hi>William Aſpley.</hi> 1616.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="sermon">
                  <pb facs="tcp:15437:92"/>
                  <pb n="179" facs="tcp:15437:92"/>
                  <epigraph>
                     <bibl>GEN: 15. 15.</bibl>
                     <q>But thou ſhalt goe to thy Fathers in peace; and ſhalt be buried in a good age.</q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the premi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of this Chap. there paſſed a co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenant be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene God and <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> a couenant confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by a ceremonie, an ancient ceremonie of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiding
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:15437:93"/> of beaſts in pieces and going through the parts of them ſo diuided, ſignifying thereby that they ſhould bee ſo diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and broken in pieces who ſhould firſt breake the couenant. So we doe finde that couenant ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed in the 34. of <hi>Ier.</hi> the 18. verſe. And ſo did Almightie God vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe to couenant with <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi> in this place in the 9. verſe before my text: after the manner of men: But when <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> had diuided the beaſts and God preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the fire had paſſed betweene the parts of the ſame, there fell out two accidents that were
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:15437:93"/> not ordinarie, firſt the text ſaith that the foules of the aire did light vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the parts of the beaſts &amp; <hi>Abraham</hi> draue them away in the 11. verſe, ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifying thereby, how the Egyptians ſhould pray vpon <hi>Abrahams</hi> poſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, the children of <hi>Iſrael:</hi> and yet notwithſtanding for <hi>Abrahams</hi> ſake, God afterward would deliuer them. Secondly, it is ſaid that there fell a heauie ſleepe vpon <hi>Abraham:</hi> &amp; that is now expreſſed in theſe words that I haue read vnto you: ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifying the death of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham:</hi> that howſoeuer hereafter his poſteritie might happily remaine
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:15437:94"/> in the land of Egypt: yet hee ſhould go to his Fathers in peace, and ſhould bee buried in a good age: ſo then you ſee that theſe words doe contain a moſt comfort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able promiſe, and a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie of <hi>Abrahams</hi> death. Death is ſorrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful in it ſelfe as being ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible vnto nature, but ſuch a death is comfort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, ſo you ſee my text is like vnto the occaſion of this our preſent meeting, it is a mixture or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound of ſorrow and comfort well tempered together, wherein I will deſire you to conſider, Firſt the perſon whom this doth concerne, it
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:15437:94"/> was <hi>Abraham:</hi> Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the condition of his death, which is here pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſied; Firſt that it is ſeaſonable, in reſpect of the circumſtances, as my text hath reference to the premiſes, thus and thus ſhall thy poſteritie fare, but thou ſhalt bee in thy graue before thou ſee that. Secondly, in regard of death it ſelfe, it was a bleſſed death; bleſſed in two reſpects. In reſpect of his ſoule firſt, for <hi>hee ſhould go to his Fathers,</hi> and the manner how, in peace: Secondly, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of his body alſo, that it ſhould bee buried, in a good age, and theſe are the branches as you
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:15437:95"/> ſee them lie in the text, <hi>But thou ſhalt go to thy fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in peace, and ſhalt bee buried in a good age:</hi> and of theſe briefely becauſe the time will permit no long diſcourſe; We muſt firſt beginne with the perſon, for elſe I ſhall make vnto you at this time but a groundleſſe ſpeech; For this is a ſure rule as the perſon is, ſuch is the death of the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon: the perſon was <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham;</hi> Father <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> the Father of the faithfull, and as hee was called a father, ſo like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe was he a patterne &amp; example of all godlie vertues vnto all poſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; a patterne of faith &amp;
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:15437:95"/> religion, the father of the faithfull. How his faith hath beene tried I ſhall not neede to particula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe; And whereſoeuer he came, or into what countrie or place ſoeuer he was ſent we ſhall read <hi>Abraham</hi> built there an Altar, to ſhew his religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and worſhip of God, amongſt heathens and Infidels. A patterne of true obedience, that whereſoeuer God called him to any countrie hee was readie to goe obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently, euen to the offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vp of his owne ſonne at Gods commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; A patterne of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militie, of meekeneſſe and mildeneſſe, of pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:15437:96"/> and of a peaceable diſpoſition; When his ſeruants and the ſeruants of <hi>Lot</hi> could not agree, how hee intreated for peace betweene them. A patterne of loue and of kindneſſe, vnto all, euen to the very <hi>Sodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mites</hi> themſelues, how affectionately doth hee perſwade with Almighty God, and pray for <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome</hi> and <hi>Gomorah:</hi> euen as though it had been for his owne ſoule: Perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture there bee ſome righteous within the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie wilt thou not ſpare the reſt for their ſakes, or if there be thus many or thus few, and ſo goes as lowe till he goes beyond
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:15437:96"/> all proportion: A pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne of righteouſneſſe and good dealing with all men. For although faith was imputed vnto <hi>Abraham</hi> for righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, yet faith went not without righteouſneſſe, No, <hi>Pharaoh</hi> himſelfe ſhall looſe nothing by <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham.</hi> A patterne of Charitie, his ſeate and place was in the tent doore, hee did not hide himſelfe, and locke the doores, and ſhut them after him, but he was rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die to receiue thoſe, that ſtood in neede to bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhed. A patterne of fatherly prouidence in his owne houſ-hold pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiding for the ſame to
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:15437:97"/> the vttermoſt of his power; Marrying his ſon a little before his death, when he was old, hee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed and admoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his ſonnes, from time to time, <hi>I know</hi> ſaith God <hi>Abraham will teach his children.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>As hee was the father of the faithfull, ſo he was a patterne and example of all godly vertues vnto poſterities. Thus you haue heard what he was. Now will you heare briefely what became of him; Hee muſt die, but his death it was a ſeaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able death, it was a time<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly death. Seaſonable in two reſpects, Firſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he ſhould be taken
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:15437:97"/> away, before his eyes did ſee thoſe afflictions which God ment to ſend vpon his poſteritie. The children of Iſrael ſhall be thus in affliction in Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt, but thou ſhalt goe to thy fathers in peace; his poſterity ſhould bee afflicted, but not for <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brahams</hi> ſake, they may thanke themſelues, for that, they ſhall bee carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into Aegypt for their owne ſinnes, but deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered out of Aegypt for <hi>Abrahams</hi> ſake, and his eies ſhall not ſee their af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction, becauſe hee was no cauſe of it. A bleſſing that God doth promiſe vnto his Saints, and hee doth beſtow this bleſſing
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:15437:98"/> vpon diuers of his ſaints, as <hi>Iſay</hi> ſheweth in the 57. chap. 1. verſe, <hi>The righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous man is taken away, and no man vnderſtandeth that hee is taken from the euill to come,</hi> and ſo God promiſed to <hi>Ioſiah</hi> the 2. of the Chron. 34. and the 28. verſe, That hee ſhould goe to his Fathers in peace, and his eyes ſhould not ſee the euill which almightie God purpoſed to bring vpon that place. Secondly, <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brahams</hi> death it was ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable and timely, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it was after the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenant which now was made betweene God and him, God had made a couenant in this chapter
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:15437:98"/> with <hi>Abraham:</hi> that hee would bee his ſure buc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kler and exceeding great reward, therefore now <hi>Abraham</hi> might depart in peace when God and hee were ſo reconciled. Now <hi>Abraham</hi> may cheerefully go to his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; After that old <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meon</hi> had embraced his Sauiour and had gotten Chriſt in his armes. Then he ſings <hi>Lord now letteſt thou thy ſeruant de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part in peace for mine eies haue ſeene thy ſaluation;</hi> Therefore ſeaſonable was the death of <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> both in that it did preuent the euill to come that he ſhould not ſee it, and alſo becauſe it was
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:15437:99"/> after the couenant, that paſſed betweene God &amp; him; and there muſt needes follow in the next place a moſt bleſſed death, expreſſed well in the phraſe of going to his Fathers, which muſt not bee vnderſtood of his bodily buriall for <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi> was buried in the field of <hi>Ephron</hi> the 25. of this booke the 10. verſe, where none of his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers were buried, and ſo the like phraſe is vſed in the 32. of Deuter: the 50. verſe where it is ſaid that <hi>Moſes</hi> was gathered to his Fathers, and yet it is ſaid likewiſe in the 34. of Deut. the Sepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher was not knowne,
<pb n="193" facs="tcp:15437:99"/> therefore of neceſſitie this phraſe muſt onely haue relation to the ſoule and ſpirit of <hi>Abraham;</hi> that, that was gathered to the ſocietie and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of thoſe holy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, that went before: thou ſhalt goe vnto thy Fathers, for there is a companie and ſociety of Saints.</p>
                  <p>Indeede when men are taken out of compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie here on earth, in this world, they goe to a better companie and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cietie of bleſſed ſoules and ſpirits in heauen; a companie where there is no diſtraction or diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, no ambition, or emulation, no ſtrife nor
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:15437:100"/> contention, but where there is peace, ioy, and pleaſure for euermore: vnto this companie and ſocietie of bleſſed ſpirits did the ſpirit of <hi>Abraham</hi> goe, and what a comfort is it (Beloued) vnto a faithfull ſoule to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der what companie and ſociety it is going vnto, when it departeth out of this life, if it bee within the couenant, if the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenant haue paſſed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene God and vs, then when wee die wee ſhall goe vnto this place, when wee go to our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, to the ſociety and fellowſhippe of the Saints of God, that wee are at reſt with <hi>Abraham,</hi>
                     <pb n="195" facs="tcp:15437:100"/> where we ſhall inioy the companie and ſocietie of all the Saints of God, that euer haue beene de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the world to this preſent time and here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after of all thoſe that ſhall come vnto the ſame place, to the end of the world. Where <hi>Eliah</hi> ſhall knowe <hi>Moſes:</hi> and <hi>Moſes Eliah,</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre together as on mount Tabour, al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>though they did liue in ſeuerall ages of the world. <hi>Peter</hi> the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle of our Sauiour Chriſt, when hee did ſee but the leaſt glimpes of this comfort, when hee ſee but two of the Saints
<pb n="196" facs="tcp:15437:101"/> 
                     <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Eliah</hi> on mount Tabour hee was ſo rauiſhed with ioy, that he cries out, <hi>Let vs build three Tabernacles.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And it is indeede to bee obſerued that the two chiefeſt Apoſtles of our Sauiour Chriſt, that is <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Paul,</hi> God did afford them this pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiledge, that they had both a taſt of the ioyes of heauen, liuing in this life, to the end they might more effectually perſwade men, to lift vp their affections to that comfortable ſociety in the world to come, <hi>Paul</hi> was rapt vp into the third heauen, and ſo ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſhed with ioy that hee
<pb n="197" facs="tcp:15437:101"/> knew not whether hee had his bodie about him or no: and methinkes after hee comes downe againe out of heauen, he writes and eſteemes of theſe worldly things as of dung, ſuch a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible reſpect hee hath of any thing vnder the Sunne after hee had taſted once of the ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of Paradiſe: For imagine it were poſſible, for a man to bee lifted vp in his body whither <hi>Paul</hi> was to the third heauen, that he might be admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted but to looke into pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radiſe, to the bleſſed ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety of bleſſed Angells, and Saints, and looke but downe againe and
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:15437:102"/> ſee this earth hanging like a Clodde beneath, and ſee ſo many milli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of men, buſied a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout nothing like Ants in a mole-hill, methinkes afterward hee ſhould ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer eſteeme of this world being rauiſhed with this companie of the Saints in heauen. And beſide <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> (except it were onely <hi>Iude</hi> that writes but one ſhort Chapter) I thinke there was not any of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles of our Sauiour Chriſt, that hath vſed ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>exhortations to the Church of God in their Epiſtles, but they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues of purpoſe did taſte ſome part of this
<pb n="199" facs="tcp:15437:102"/> glorie, to the end they might the more power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully eleuate the hearts of men; <hi>Paul</hi> in the third heauen, and <hi>Peter, Iames</hi> and <hi>Iohn</hi> on mount Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour all of them ſee a glimpes of this glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Go vnto thy fathers,</hi> ſo did <hi>Abraham,</hi> in Spirit he went vnto his Fathers that were dead before him and his ſonnes after, they came vnto him. Then the manner and the paſſage vnto this place is expreſſed in the text, <hi>Thou ſhalt goe vnto thy Fathers in peace.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now you muſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand whoſoeuer di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in peace muſt die in
<pb n="200" facs="tcp:15437:103"/> Chriſt, for there is no true peace without Chriſt, <hi>Abraham</hi> died many hundred yeeres before Chriſt was borne, and yet our Sauiour Chriſt ſaith of <hi>Abraham,</hi> in the eight of <hi>Iohn</hi> the 58. verſe that <hi>Abraham</hi> ſaw his daies and reioyc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, hee ſaw him then in the eyes of faith.</p>
                  <p>Hee died, therefore in the faith of Chriſt and ſo died in peace, for Chriſt is the Prince of peace that conferreth true peace vpon all his Saints, hee is the Oliue tree of peace whereon peace groweth, the eleuenth to the <hi>Romans</hi> the twentie-four, Like that doue
<pb n="201" facs="tcp:15437:103"/> with the Oliue branch in her mouth, hee euer brought peace with him, it was his ordinary ſalu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation when hee was on the earth, peace be vnto you, it was his legacie left with his Church when he went out of the world, <hi>my peace I leaue with you;</hi> Therefore <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi> dying in the peace of Chriſt, muſt needes die in peace of conſcience, and as in peace of conſcience ſo likewiſe in a moſt peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able maner. In the 25. of Geneſ. the eight verſe, it is ſaid <hi>Abraham</hi> did yeeld vp his ſpirit, his ſpirit was not taken from him by violence but hee
<pb n="202" facs="tcp:15437:104"/> did moſt willingly yeeld vp his ſpirit into the hands of God. Oh how fearefull is the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of death to thoſe that are not in Chriſt? that fearefull rending of the ſoule and bodie a ſunder is moſt terrible vnto them; but the death of <hi>Abraham,</hi> it was like that ſleepe which was ſpoken of before this verſe, that ſignified his death, a heauie ſleep fell vpon <hi>Abraham,</hi> for ſo likewiſe fell death vp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on him, euen as if nature ſhould haue falne a ſleepe, quietly, meeke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, peaceably, and this is for his ſoule.</p>
                  <p>Then it followeth in
<pb n="203" facs="tcp:15437:104"/> the next place, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning his bodie, that that alſo ſhould bee buried in a good age. Euen for to bee buried it is a bleſſing, and a bleſſing that euery man doth not enioy. No <hi>Iehoiakim</hi> himſelfe, though hee were a King, in the 22. of Ieremy the 19 verſe, ſhall bee buried like an aſſe drawne and caſt forth on a dunghill, as <hi>Ioſephus</hi> alſo writes of him. It is threatned by <hi>Salomon</hi> that thoſe who are diſobedient to their parents, the rauens of the valleyes ſhall picke out their eyes. And thoſe that are treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to the Ciuill Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates,
<pb n="204" facs="tcp:15437:105"/> wee ſee they are made a ſpectacle to the world, and depriued of buriall and ſet vp in the aire and made a prey to the foules of the aire: as this is a iudgement on theſe, ſo likewiſe the other is a bleſſing on them, that goe vnto the graue in peace, and it is an honour that is due vnto the very bodies of the Saints of God, ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they are the worke of Gods hands; not as the bodies of beaſts, which God did make as it were with a word after a more ſleight maner, but for mans bodie hee for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med it not onely with his word, but it is the
<pb n="205" facs="tcp:15437:105"/> tabernacle of an heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſubſtance, thats the ſoule, which is the image of God, becauſe our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily nature is alſo aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med into the diuine na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture at the incarnation of the Sonne of GOD. Becauſe the bodies of the Saints are the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of Chriſt, and the temples of the HOLY GHOST; <hi>Know you not</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>that your bodies are the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of the Holy Ghost.</hi> And laſt of all, becauſe, though they ſleepe in the duſt for a time, yet here-after they ſhall riſe in glory and ſhine as the Sunne in glory in the kingdome of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen,
<pb n="206" facs="tcp:15437:106"/> and therfore great reaſon that ſome honor and reuerence bee done, euen vnto the very bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies of the Saints. So was <hi>Abraham</hi> buried, buried hy his two ſonnes <hi>Iſaack</hi> and <hi>Iſmael,</hi> as in the 25. chapter of this booke, the ninth verſe, buried in the field of <hi>Ephron,</hi> a ſelected grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of purpoſe, where his wife <hi>Sarah</hi> was buried long before, Geneſ: 23. 19. and his ſonnes wife <hi>Rebecca</hi> in the 49. of this booke the 31. verſe. One bleſſing more let mee adde in my Text, to <hi>Abraham,</hi> and we will come to my purpoſe. <hi>Abraham</hi> was buried in
<pb n="207" facs="tcp:15437:106"/> a good age, for ſo God did promiſe, and it was propheſied in this place, and ſo performed in the 25. of this booke the 8. verſe, and there wee finde the place amplifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in three phraſes to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, for euermore the performance of God is with the largeſt. The promiſe is like a ſeede ſowne in the ground onely, but the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance comes in like fruit that's multiplied &amp; caried in, in due ſeaſon: ſo it is ſaid that <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> was buried, he died in a good age, an olde man of great yeares: here is three phraſes to expreſſe one thing, and
<pb n="208" facs="tcp:15437:107"/> it is no idle repetition; he died in a good age, ſo good as hee deſired to liue no longer, nor did he deſire for to die any ſooner: he liued to ſettle his houſhold in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, to marrie his ſonne <hi>Iſaack,</hi> to prepare his ſoule for God and to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part in peace, <hi>A good age.</hi> Secondly, <hi>he dyed an old man;</hi> If hee had liued any longer his daies would but haue beene troubleſome and bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denſome vnto himſelfe. <hi>An old man;</hi> ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> not old before his time, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a third phraſe is ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, <hi>an old man of great yeares;</hi> and ſo did <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> die and was gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb n="209" facs="tcp:15437:107"/> to his people. <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> liued but threeſcore and ten yeares, and yet <hi>Dauid</hi> was old before his time.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, <hi>hee died in good yeares:</hi> this God promiſed to <hi>Abraham,</hi> and this God hath per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, ſo as that was verified of him, that is promiſed to the Saints in the 5. of Iob the 25. verſe, that they go vnto their graue as a ricke of come that goes into the barne; when the Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are white vnto the harueſt, as our Sauiour Chriſt ſpeaketh, ſo ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Hebrew text it is here as we ſay, <hi>in a good age.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="210" facs="tcp:15437:108"/>
                  <p> When the Regions are white vnto the har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſt, then the ſickle of death is put in in due ſeaſon and they carried to the euer-laſting barnes.</p>
                  <p>What bleſſing was there then that <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> did want, hee was taken away before the affliction of his poſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie came, yet not before the couenant was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed betweene GOD and him, all this was granted him, and hee dyed an ould man full of yeeres. And thus be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued haue you heard of <hi>Abraham</hi> what he was and what is become of him.</p>
                  <pb n="211" facs="tcp:15437:108"/>
                  <p> May it pleaſe you now a little for to turne your thoughts vpon one of the ſonnes of <hi>Abraham,</hi> and briefely to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber with me, firſt what he was, and now what is become of him; For as hee did tread in the ſteps of his Father <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham,</hi> ſo I will treade in the ſteps of my text, concerning him, and <hi>Abraham,</hi> hee was the ſonne of <hi>Abraham</hi> while he liued, the bleſſing of <hi>Abraham</hi> was vpon him at his death, and ſo I make no doubt but hee doth reſt in <hi>Abrahams</hi> boſome, <hi>Abraham</hi> the father of the faithfull a patterne of faith and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion
<pb n="212" facs="tcp:15437:109"/> vnto his ſonnes and poſteritie, this was one of them.</p>
                  <p>It was his chiefe ſtay and comfort euer in his great heauineſſe, and in his ſickneſſe long before his death, or before that deadly ſicknes, the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenant that paſſeth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene GOD and his Saints, in Chriſt Ieſus, there was his ſtay. <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> was a patterne of faith; faith was imputed vnto him for righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, but it neuer went without righteouſneſſe: no more did his, I doe refer him for that to you that haue had ſo many yeres experience of him, did this our brother do
<pb n="213" facs="tcp:15437:109"/> any man wrong willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly? was hee not an vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right and a iuſt man in all his dealing, with all whom hee had to doe withall?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Abraham</hi> was a pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne of humilitie, of meeknes, of mildneſſe, of patience, and of a quiet and peaceable diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, and ſo was he, witnes this Pariſh, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he hath liued. How deadly any contention or debate amongſt vs was vnto his ſoule and ſpirit, how diligent would he be, and how troubled, till the peace were made, bleſſed are the peace-makers.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Araham</hi> was a pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne
<pb n="214" facs="tcp:15437:110"/> of loue and kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of kinde affection vnto all men: and ſo was he ready and prone to ſhew his kindnes ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his eſtate vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on any occaſion.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Abraham</hi> was a pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne of charitie, ſo was he; for I haue obſerued (comming to this mans table at ordinarie occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions) who were his gueſts commonly, but ſuch as were not able to bid him againe? ſuch as had moſt neede of refreſhing, like <hi>Lazarus</hi> in <hi>Abrahams</hi> boſome.</p>
                  <p>He was a patterne of fatherly prouidence in his familie, and to his children. <hi>I know</hi> (ſaith
<pb n="215" facs="tcp:15437:110"/> God) <hi>that Abraham will teach his ſonnes,</hi> and ſo did hee, hee did conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually admoniſh them; and if any admonition at any time did not take that effect hee deſired, how grieuous it was to his ſoule and ſpirit, let his Sonnes remember it now he is gone, and if any affliction come vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them, as on <hi>Abrahams</hi> poſteritie, let them thank themſelues, it was not the Fathers fault, they ſhall fare the better for his ſake; <hi>Abrahams</hi> po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteritie were not afflicted in Egypt for his ſake, but deliuered out of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt for <hi>Abrahams</hi> ſake, but he is gone, hee is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
<pb n="216" facs="tcp:15437:111"/> away ſeaſonablely from the euill that is to come, the ſinnes of theſe times do propheſie ſome euill to come vpon vs, and it is a bleſſing vnto them that are taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way before it comes. He is gone to enioy the effect of that couenant made betweene God and his Saints, in Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, that was his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, he is gone vnto his Fathers, and if his Sons will tread in his ſteps, they ſhall goe to their Fathers; he is gone and hath left this companie, this companie now pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, whereof hee was a good member, and is gone vnto an other com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie
<pb n="217" facs="tcp:15437:111"/> of the Saints and Angels of God in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, hee is gone in peace, in that manner that his death was a ſlee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping in death in peace of conſcience. In a pea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceable manner did hee depart this life, euen as if hee had ſtolne a nap: wee that were then pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent with him could not tell when he went; and now beloued are wee here aſſembled for to ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnize his Funerall in that decent manner you ſee, and that is beſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to follow, and to remember the Saints of God that are taken away from amongſt vs. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi> hee was buried,
<pb n="218" facs="tcp:15437:112"/> and hee was buried in the ground where hee had buried his beloued wife <hi>Sarai</hi> before, and ſo is hee. Innocent hee was in his life, innocent as a doue, hee hath con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued this many yeeres, ſolitarie as a turtle doue, and now hee is gone, yet ſo many yeeres af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, as I thinke one graue may well hold them both. Laſt of all, let me adde the concluſion of my text, he is buried in a good age. I may adde the three phraſes before mentioned of Abraham, <hi>A good age, an old man, of great yeeres;</hi> if he had liued longer, as I haue often heard him ſay vnto
<pb n="219" facs="tcp:15437:112"/> mee, hee ſhould haue beene burdenſome and troubleſome vnto him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, a good age, foure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcore &amp; one, a good age in theſe times, but let me yet add one thing more, as hee died <hi>in a good age,</hi> ſo I may ſay truely that hee died vpon a good day alſo, for it was vpon the Saboth day in the morning, that hee commended his ſoule into the hands of God, in the morning when we were about to aſſemble in this place to praiſe God, then did hee ſing <hi>Halleluiah</hi> with the ſaints and Angells in heauen. No man did more duly obſerue Gods ſaboths in
<pb n="220" facs="tcp:15437:113"/> this place them hee did, and now his ſoule doth enioy that ſaboth of reſt, in the kingdome of hea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uen. On the Sabboth day in the morning did he goe to ſolemnize the Sabboth in heauen, a Sabboth without an euen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing, that is an eternall reſt, into this reſt is hee now entred, and into this reſt that we in due time may alſo enter, that our ſpirits may enioy the bleſſed companie of all the Saints of God, let vs deſire of him who hath purchaſed the ſame Sabboth for vs, IESVS CHRIST the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous; To whom with the Father &amp; bleſſed Spirit,
<pb n="221" facs="tcp:15437:113"/> one euerliuing and only wiſe God, be aſcribed all praiſe, power &amp; thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuing this day and for euermore</p>
                  <closer>Amen.</closer>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
